<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Matter | Home Assistant]]></title>
  <link href="https://ivangrod.github.io/blog/categories/matter/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://ivangrod.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2025-09-23T17:43:39+00:00</updated>
  <id>https://ivangrod.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Home Assistant]]></name>
    
  </author>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Home Assistant officially Matters]]></title>
    <link href="https://ivangrod.github.io/blog/2025/03/10/matter-certification/"/>
    <updated>2025-03-10T00:00:01+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://ivangrod.github.io/blog/2025/03/10/matter-certification</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src='/images/blog/2025-03-matter-certification/art.jpg' alt="Home Assistant is officially matter certified" class='no-shadow' /></p>
<p>Matter in Home Assistant has been officially certified! 🎉 The Connectivity Standards Alliance (CSA) has certified <a href="https://csa-iot.org/csa_product/home-assistant/">Home Assistant</a> and the <a href="https://csa-iot.org/csa_product/open-home-foundation-matter-server/">Open Home Foundation Matter Server</a>, the first open-source project to receive this certification. Certification is proof that open source projects can sit among, or even above, big tech when it comes to providing the best smart home experience.</p>
<p>Home Assistant, as part of the <a href="https://www.openhomefoundation.org/">Open Home Foundation</a>, strongly believes in open standards. They embody our values of choice, privacy, and sustainability in the smart home. When a standard is well supported, consumers get access to a wide range of smart home devices that should work far into the future, which is great for sustainability. Best of all, they work locally, keeping your smart home data in your home.</p>
<p>All these benefits led us to include open standards certification <a href="/blog/2024/06/12/roadmap-2024h1/#open-standards-certified-quality">in our roadmap</a>. Home Assistant’s implementations of Matter, Zigbee, and Z-Wave are already industry-leading, so it only makes sense to clearly signal and give users peace of mind that we provide true compatibility. This most recent certification is not just big for Home Assistant, but read on to see how it also helps any open source project looking to use Matter.</p>
<!--more-->
<h2>Matter matters</h2>
<p class="img"><lite-youtube videoid="rEugjMk-4II" videotitle="State of Matter 2024"></lite-youtube>Our live stream from 2024 explains Matter in depth</p>
<p>Matter is the latest smart home open standard, which is looking to connect and control smart home devices regardless of their manufacturer or which ecosystem you want to control them from. Like the other open standards we support, it can be controlled fully locally, meaning these devices are not reliant on the cloud to work. The Connectivity Standards Alliance (CSA) is the body behind the Matter standard, representing its many members. They certify devices and set the rules on how they work together.</p>
<p>If you’re not familiar with Matter, I’m not surprised. Though its adoption is growing, it’s only a <a href="https://csa-iot.org/newsroom/matter-arrives/">couple of years old</a>. The most important companies in the smart home space have joined this standard, but support is still growing and becoming more consistent. If it fulfills its promise, any smart home product should work with your ecosystem of choice, and that makes us optimistic about its future.</p>
<p>More and more Matter devices are entering the market, and if you’re buying new smart devices, it will just be a matter of time 😉 before you own one. To this point, Matter devices are even a part of our <a href="https://partner.home-assistant.io/">Works With Home Assistant</a> program. <a href="/blog/2024/09/03/aqara-joins-works-with-home-assistant/">Aqara was the first</a> to join our program with Matter devices, and we tested these devices ourselves to ensure they give the best experience possible in Home Assistant. This year, we expect many more Matter devices to join the program, and we should have more updates soon.</p>
<p>From a technical perspective, Matter is really interesting—it can work with different smart home systems at the same time. It also keeps the way devices connect and communicate separate, allowing it to connect to devices over Wi-Fi, Ethernet, and <a href="/integrations/thread/">Thread</a> (a new mesh network technology for smart devices). Read our <a href="/blog/2024/01/25/matter-livestream-blog/">State of Matter blog</a> or watch Paulus’ appearance on <a href="https://youtu.be/0Y75XEXAXfY?si=nSDpP6THkWhkARuc&amp;t=3493">the Vergecast Matter Holiday Spec-Tacular</a> for a deeper dive into the standard.</p>
<h2>What certification brings</h2>
<p class="img"><img src='/images/blog/2025-03-matter-certification/ha-matter.png' alt="Home Assistant Matter certification"/>Well, this is a bit... awesome</p>
<p>First and foremost, from a usability perspective, nothing will change for you. We are consistently the first to adopt the newest Matter versions, currently providing the highest version available. We’ll keep on improving the Matter Server and the Matter integration at the same pace, ensuring that all device types in the Matter spec will work perfectly with Home Assistant—just from now on it will come with this certification badge.</p>
<p>The <a href="https://csa-iot.org/csa_product/open-home-foundation-matter-server/">Open Home Foundation Matter Server</a> is now an officially trusted/certified software component, while <a href="https://csa-iot.org/csa_product/home-assistant/">Home Assistant</a> is a certified “User Interface Component” (more on this distinction below). This allows us to clearly show this with a logo, along with being listed on the Matter website. For new Home Assistant users, this helps build confidence, knowing it is a supported way to use Matter. Similarly, for brands that don’t know much about Home Assistant, these references can be surprisingly helpful, and it’s our goal to have more brands target Home Assistant in their development. Another handy part of being certified is getting more access to pre-test new devices and SDK revisions, which will help development going forward.</p>
<h3>Why two certifications (and the server add-on)</h3>
<p class="img"><img src='/images/blog/2025-03-matter-certification/ohf-matter.png' alt="Open Home Foundation Matter Server is certified"/>So much fun we did it twice</p>
<p>If you’re confused why we certified both Home Assistant and Open Home Foundation Matter Server, there are a couple of legal/procedural reasons, but it comes with some useful benefits. We certified the server as a standalone component to allow any project to use it. Each project that uses it, including Home Assistant, will have to go through a certification process to acknowledge that it uses a certified component as a “User Interface Component”. Certification for the Open Home Foundation Matter Server means it properly connects and communicates with other Matter devices, while certification for Home Assistant is about being able to display the Matter trademark.</p>
<p>This separation is important because it means that we won’t need to go through recertification every time we update Home Assistant. This way we can keep the Matter-related backend isolated in both a software and certification sense. This is also why we will need to continue to have the Open Home Foundation Matter Server as an add-on, and it cannot be built into <a href="/installation/#about-installation-methods">Home Assistant Core</a>.</p>
<h2>The road to certification</h2>
<p>Becoming Matter certified was not easy. When we started certification, the process was tooled up to test and certify devices, not Matter controllers, let alone completely software-based (and open source) controllers. We chose to collaborate with <a href="https://www.resillion.com/services/conformance-interoperability/wireless-product-testing/matter-certification/">Resillion</a> for our certification. They are a testing and certification house based in Belgium with a lot of experience certifying Matter products. They do the formal testing and submit the results to the CSA. Together, we collaborated to write thousands of lines of test scripts, ensuring that as many test cases as possible were automated.</p>
<p class="img"><img src='/images/blog/2025-03-matter-certification/lab.jpg' alt="Marcel van der Veldt at the Resillion lab"/>My visit to Resillion's lab, I brought my own lab coat</p>
<p>We really appreciate Resillion for taking on this challenge. Not only were we the first controller they certified, but we also went for all the device types in the Matter 1.3 specification. This was a huge effort for all involved, but now that these test scripts exist, they only require minor updates for each new version; we can reuse them whenever we need to recertify.</p>
<div class="alert">
    <p>“At Resillion, we strongly support interoperability in connected home technology, and assure, secure and innovate to help make this technology work for everyone. For us, this was not only a fantastic way to contribute to the Home Assistant open-source project, but also upgrade our own Home Assistant instances with Matter, as enthusiasts of the project running active instances of HA in our own homes.</p>
    <p>“Working on a controller utilizing the full Matter 1.3 feature set presents a great opportunity to advance HA and Matter, and we look forward to supporting the developed codebase and further contributing to an open smart home.”</p>
    <em style="text-align: right; display: block;">- Jan Claes, Head of testing services - C&I Global, Resillion</em>
</div>
<p>This is another example of something that’s only possible because of the support we get from users subscribing to <a href="/cloud/">Home Assistant Cloud</a>. Certification would be very difficult for any other open-source project, but we have the funding first to build a great server and also to pay for the required testing. Now this open source implementation exists and can be used by any project looking to add Matter.</p>
<h2>The future Matters</h2>
<p>As we continue improving our Matter implementation, the Matter standard itself is also evolving. Even with the progress it has made in the past year, there are still challenges to overcome. Matter is completely built on IPv6, and its rollout is uncovering the poor state of IPv6 support in today’s network hardware. Also, as it’s a complicated standard, it can be difficult to explain concepts like Thread and Fabrics to the average user, but hopefully users won’t need to be experts in the future to get the most out of Matter in their homes.</p>
<p>Some might call Matter the smart home standard to replace all others, but we believe that there’s room for multiple standards, each providing its own unique benefits. We are focused on providing the highest support for all local smart home standards (<a href="/blog/2024/11/15/roadmap-2024h2/#open-protocols">certifying other standards is on our roadmap</a>) and ensuring they work far into the future, which is great for consumer choice and sustainability.</p>
<p>As Home Assistant grows and takes important steps like certification, the more credibility we gain in the industry—it’s a virtuous circle that helps us and Open Home projects continuously improve. Thanks for your support and helping us make this possible 🙏.</p>
<p><strong>Try the Matter in Home Assistant today:</strong>
<a href="https://my.home-assistant.io/redirect/config_flow_start?domain=matter"><img src='https://my.home-assistant.io/badges/config_flow_start.svg' style='border: 0;box-shadow: none;' alt="!Open your Home Assistant instance and show the dashboard of an add-on."></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The State of Matter]]></title>
    <link href="https://ivangrod.github.io/blog/2024/01/25/matter-livestream-blog/"/>
    <updated>2024-01-25T00:00:01+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://ivangrod.github.io/blog/2024/01/25/matter-livestream-blog</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>During our State of Matter live stream two weeks ago, we explained what Matter is, how it relates to Thread, and how you can compare it with existing protocols you may already know, like Zigbee or Z-Wave.</p>
<p>In this blog post, we’ve extracted the highlights of the stream for you. We also link to our updated <a href="/integrations/matter/">Matter</a> and <a href="/integrations/thread/">Thread</a> documentation where relevant.</p>
<p>You can watch the entire live stream here:</p>
<p><lite-youtube videoid="rEugjMk-4II" videotitle="State of Matter"></lite-youtube></p>
<p>We’ll also highlight each segment of the live stream in this blog under each corresponding heading, so you can start watching the specific parts that interest you!</p>
<!--more-->
<h2>Why we believe in Matter</h2>
<p><lite-youtube videoid="rEugjMk-4II" videoStartAt="213" videotitle="State of Matter"></lite-youtube></p>
<p>We believe in Matter: it’s open source, and most importantly, it’s fully local by default. Matter will allow us to control devices ranging from lights, to robot vacuums, to TVs, and to many other IP-connected devices, all through a standardized protocol. It is a huge step forward towards having more sustainable and worry-free smart home products. For this reason, Nabu Casa uses the revenue we get from the subscribers to Home Assistant Cloud (thank you all!) to employ developers who are dedicated to implementing Matter. And we have even joined the Connectivity Standards Alliance (CSA) - the organization behind the Matter standard - as a participant to have a front-row seat and to defend the <a href="/blog/2021/12/23/the-open-home/">Open Home values</a> during the development of the standard.</p>
<p>Matter launched only one year ago, compared to twenty years for a standard like Zigbee, so it’s important to account for that in your expectations. If you’ve already invested heavily in an existing local standard, like Zigbee or Z-Wave, Matter is probably not your best choice at this point. We think there is no reason to throw these current smart home devices out, especially when they still work fine - after all, sustainability is one of our <a href="/blog/2021/12/23/the-open-home/">Open Home values</a>. But if you are new to the smart home scene and looking for devices with local, cloud-free standards that will still work even many years from now, keep an eye on Matter. The standard is rapidly evolving, with major updates twice a year where new device types and enhancements to existing ones are released.</p>
<p>After this first year, the current selection of Matter devices is still a bit limited, but a lot of companies have been using this time to develop them, and we expect more to be released soon. More and more companies are <a href="https://csa-iot.org/members/">joining the CSA</a> and taking up the standard every month. We think Matter is here to stay and is going to be widely adopted.</p>
<h2>Demystifying Matter</h2>
<p><lite-youtube videoid="rEugjMk-4II" videoStartAt="525" videotitle="State of Matter"></lite-youtube></p>
<p>To really understand what we’re talking about when it comes to Matter, we recommend you read our <a href="/integrations/matter/">updated Matter documentation</a> or watch this chapter from our live stream.</p>
<p><img src='/images/blog/2024-01-matter/matter-diagram.png' class='no-shadow' /></p>
<p>In this segment, our product manager JLo explains Matter in an easy-to-understand, visual manner, using the diagram you see above. You’ll no longer have to wonder about Thread, Border routers, Bridges, or other Matter terminology after you’ve watched this video.</p>
<h2>The current state of Matter in Home Assistant</h2>
<p>For the past year, we have been working on getting the foundation ready to support Matter devices in Home Assistant. Our implementation is based on the official Matter SDK, and we plan for it to become officially certified by the CSA to show that it will work problem-free with all products that carry the Matter logo. But we are not there yet; that is why we still label Matter as Beta in the integrations list. This will not change until our implementation has been certified.</p>
<p>We are still ironing out bugs, writing documentation, adding missing features, and doing a lot of troubleshooting. We are not alone on this, as many manufacturers needed this first year to get comfortable with the new standard as well, resulting in some unstable early devices coming to the market. We’ve also had to tweak our Home Assistant Operating System to work well with Matter, Thread, and its IPv6 requirement.</p>
<p>It has been a bumpy - sometimes even frustrating - ride, but everything is slowly getting into good shape. Vendors have ironed out bugs in their Matter device firmware, all kinds of new devices are popping up in stores, and the Matter 1.1 and 1.2 updates brought tons of stability fixes to the standard.</p>
<p>From our perspective, it’s amazing that Matter is already in this state after being started only a couple of years ago. You can clearly see the enormous power of so many companies, from small to big, believing in Matter and working together to improve it.</p>
<h3>Get started with Matter in Home Assistant</h3>
<p><lite-youtube videoid="rEugjMk-4II" videoStartAt="2652" videotitle="State of Matter"></lite-youtube></p>
<p>If you want to get started with Matter in Home Assistant, it is really important that you read the <a href="/integrations/matter/">documentation</a> or watch this chapter of our live stream, which covers it all.</p>
<p>Matter has a few gotcha’s you should know about, and because we are still in the Beta stage, not everything is as polished as we want it to be.</p>
<p>If you follow the requirements/recommendations in the documentation, you will see that there are four scenarios that are stable and work well in Home Assistant today:</p>
<ul>
<li>Using WiFi-based Matter devices, like TP-Link (Matter) power plugs.</li>
<li>Using Matter bridges, like the Aqara M2 or SwitchBot Hub 2.</li>
<li>Using Thread-based Matter devices; if you have an Apple iPhone and one or more Apple devices that can be utilized by Home Assistant as a Thread Border router: HomePod gen2, HomePod Mini, Apple TV 4K (with ethernet).</li>
<li>Using Thread-based Matter devices; if you have an Android phone and one or more Google devices that can be utilized by Home Assistant as a Thread Border router:
Google Nest Hub v2, Google Nest Hub Max, Google Nest WiFi Pro</li>
</ul>
<p>It’s <em>very</em> important to note here that for Thread-based devices, the current recommended setup utilizes border routers from Apple or Google that match the type of phone you have. Please don’t worry - this doesn’t mean you have to add your devices to their ecosystems. Home Assistant will just use them to get access to the Thread radio network. The communication between the Home Assistant Matter controller and your Matter devices is completely encrypted and secure.</p>
<p>Using Home Assistant itself as a Thread border router (for example, by using the Thread radio in the Home Assistant Yellow or Home Assistant SkyConnect) is still under development at this point and is only recommended for the more technically experienced users. Currently, due to a bug, it can only be set up if you use an Android phone. Setting the Home Assistant SkyConnect or Home Assistant Yellow up as a Thread border router is not yet possible for users in the iOS/Apple ecosystem. We recommend that iOS users place, for example, a HomePod Mini or other Apple border router near their Thread devices to get the required Thread coverage. Alternatively, you can stay with WiFi-based Matter devices.</p>
<h3>Important</h3>
<p>You do <em>not</em> need any additional hardware or radios to work with Matter devices. Any device that is running Home Assistant Operating System, be it a Home Assistant Green, a Raspberry Pi, or any other installation, is already a fully functional Matter Controller. You can connect to WiFi-based Matter devices straight out of the box. Only if you plan to use Thread-based Matter devices do you need additional hardware in the form of a Thread border router.</p>
<h3>Our tips for a frustration-free Matter experience:</h3>
<ul>
<li>
<p>Read the <a href="/integrations/matter/">documentation</a> for Matter.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>The easiest devices to get started with are WiFi-based Matter devices and Matter bridges. Do note that many brands with Matter bridges also have excellent native integrations in Home Assistant, and these integrations may offer features not yet available in the Matter standard.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>You need to run the Home Assistant Operating System. Other installation types are not supported.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>You need a standard (flat) network. Enterprise-like network setups with VLANs, mDNS responders, etc., break the expectations that Matter has about the network and are not supported. Keep it simple, and it will just work.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Enable IPv6 on your home router and Home Assistant Operating System. You don’t need to get IPv6 from your internet provider, as the Matter devices operate locally. But you do need to make sure it’s enabled on your home network.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>If you are planning on using Thread-based Matter devices, you will need one or more <a href="/integrations/thread/">Thread border routers</a> in your home. Home Assistant can work with third-party Thread border routers from Google or Apple as well, without having to add your devices to their ecosystem.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Always check the device packaging to make sure it has a Matter badge. Thread is also used for other standards, so a device with a Thread badge on the packaging does not have to be a Matter device.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Note that Matter is still in an early stage, so not every advanced feature you are used to may currently be implemented in this standard.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Use the latest version of both Home Assistant and the Home Assistant Companion apps, as we are improving Matter support and fixing bugs continuously. Using the latest version can make the difference in being able to add a device to Home Assistant or not.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<h3>Support</h3>
<p>If you run into problems, please join our <a href="/join-chat/">Discord server</a>, where we have a dedicated Matter channel. Both our developers and many very experienced members of our community are active there to help you out with your Matter setup. Please only open an issue on our GitHub issue tracker if you encounter an actual bug.</p>
<h2>The Future of Matter in Home Assistant</h2>
<p><lite-youtube videoid="rEugjMk-4II" videoStartAt="4450" videotitle="State of Matter"></lite-youtube></p>
<p>In the near future, we are focusing on improving the user experience to onboard and manage Matter devices. Especially adding new Matter devices to Home Assistant should be as stress-free as possible.</p>
<p><img src='/images/blog/2024-01-matter/matter-roadmap.png' class='no-shadow' /></p>
<p>This is what we are focusing on now:</p>
<ul>
<li>Functionality to ‘share’ a device from Home Assistant to another Matter controller.</li>
<li>Showing basic device information and diagnostics about a device in the Home Assistant interface, as well as adding some troubleshooting options such as forcing a full interview.</li>
</ul>
<p>This is what we will be focusing on next:</p>
<ul>
<li>A simpler flow to add Matter devices (a process called commissioning), where we guide our users step-by-step all the way from unboxing a device to being able to control it in Home Assistant. For now, we are focusing on the stable scenarios we mentioned previously. This means that we are improving the commissioning flow in our companion apps, relying on the Matter functionality built into your phone, and using (if necessary) Thread networks managed by the vendor of your phone (Google or Apple).</li>
<li>A better handling of sharing of devices between controllers (a functionality called multi-admin). Adding a brand new Matter device (commissioning) and sharing a device that is already controlled by a Matter controller (multi-admin) are not part of the same flow. This difference is dictated by the Matter standard and its security features; a current controller (admin) has to allow a device to join another controller. This is often misunderstood today, and we are trying to create a better flow that guides our users toward the right path for their devices.</li>
<li>We want to implement some missing features in the current platforms, such as light transitions and scenes.</li>
</ul>
<p>This is what we want to achieve in the long run:</p>
<ul>
<li>The ability to use the Home Assistant SkyConnect or Home Assistant Yellow as a Thread border router to connect to Thread-based Matter devices instead of using Apple or Google Border routers.</li>
</ul>
<p>On top of this, we will continuously focus on extending the support for new devices as new device types are added to the specification or existing ones are extended. In some cases, manufacturers even contribute to Home Assistant themselves to ensure a new device type is supported.</p>
<p>We are also continuously keeping the quality of our Matter integration up to the standard of Home Assistant and fixing the most impactful issues our users are facing. For example, right now, we are making sure Matter devices that lose power are handled better in Home Assistant.</p>
<h2>Using Home Assistant Yellow or Home Assistant SkyConnect</h2>
<p><lite-youtube videoid="rEugjMk-4II" videoStartAt="5209" videotitle="State of Matter"></lite-youtube></p>
<p>As we mentioned while talking about the recommended scenarios earlier, using the Home Assistant Yellow or Home Assistant SkyConnect for Thread is still in development and only recommended for technically experienced users.</p>
<p>That’s why our current recommendation for Home Assistant Yellow and Home Assistant SkyConnect is to use the Zigbee firmware to power your Zigbee network. This is a stable solution that has worked reliably since the introduction of these products and offers a great experience.</p>
<p>As we continue to work on Matter in Home Assistant, we’re now focused on ensuring that the Thread experience will catch up and become a first-class citizen, making it easy to connect to your Thread-based devices in Home Assistant without a third-party Thread border router. The Thread firmware is already fully functional under the hood, but we still have some work to do to make the experience of using Thread-based devices in Home Assistant feel good. As we mentioned in our chapter on the future of Matter in Home Assistant, we expect great strides in this area within the following months. Once the experience has improved, we will recommend using this Thread firmware to power your Thread network as an alternative to using third-party Thread border routers from Apple or Google.</p>
<p>There is a third, experimental, firmware option that supports multiprotocol, which allows the Silicon Labs chip in these products to connect to both Zigbee and Thread networks with one radio. We announced our intent to release a firmware supporting multiprotocol when we launched Home Assistant Yellow and Home Assistant SkyConnect, and this firmware has been available since December 2022. It integrates the Silicon Labs SDK, which adds this support for multiprotocol. During the further development and testing of the multiprotocol firmware, we have concluded that while Silicon Labs’ multiprotocol works, it comes with technical limitations. These limitations mean users will not have the best experience compared to using dedicated Zigbee and Thread radios. That is why we do not recommend using this firmware, and it will remain an experimental feature of Home Assistant Yellow and Home Assistant SkyConnect. If you currently have the multiprotocol firmware installed but don’t actively use it to connect to Thread devices, we recommend that you <a href="https://skyconnect.home-assistant.io/procedures/disable-multiprotocol/">disable multiprotocol</a>.</p>
<p>Nothing changes for current users of the multiprotocol firmware who are happy with their experience. The experimental multiprotocol firmware will remain available, but we will not recommend it to new users. Instead, we will focus on making sure the dedicated Zigbee and Thread firmwares deliver the best experience to users.</p>
<h2>Thank you</h2>
<p>After our first year of implementing Matter, we’re very happy that the technical foundation is in good shape. We can now take the next steps to ensure the entire Matter experience is as good as it can possibly be! Thank you to all of the users who have been on this journey with us, have provided us with valuable feedback and bug reports, and have shared their experiences so we know how we can make Matter in Home Assistant even better. And thank you to all of the viewers of the live stream and everyone who sent in questions beforehand and during the stream; your input helps us make these streams the best they can be. And if you made it all the way down here - thank you for reading!</p>
<p>If you have any more questions or experience problems with Matter in Home Assistant, please join our <a href="/join-chat/">Discord server</a>! We have a dedicated Matter channel there, and our developers and many experienced members of our community can help you out.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The State of Matter livestream]]></title>
    <link href="https://ivangrod.github.io/blog/2024/01/05/matter-livestream/"/>
    <updated>2024-01-05T00:00:01+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://ivangrod.github.io/blog/2024/01/05/matter-livestream</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>TL;DR: We’ll have a Matter livestream on Wednesday, January 10. Post all your questions about Matter and Home Assistant in the comment section, and we’ll try to answer them during the stream!</p>
<p>In late 2022, Matter was first released to the public. It promised to be the new local home automation standard that would unify various manufacturers’ ecosystems and smart devices. We <a href="/blog/2023/12/04/nabu-casa-at-the-matter-member-meeting/">joined the CSA</a>, the alliance developing Matter, to have a front-row seat and make our implementation of Matter the best we can. Now, one year later, did Matter live up to its promise, and what’s the state of Matter within Home Assistant?</p>
<p>We ask this question because lately, articles about Matter in the media have turned a bit sour. Compared to older standards like Zigbee and Z-Wave, they say, Matter is not yet in good shape. But this is not an entirely fair comparison: Zigbee and Z-Wave have had many years to develop into what they are now, while Matter was released just over a year ago. A new standard will always need some time to settle in and mature.</p>
<p>Our view on Matter is both more optimistic and still realistic. We think Matter completely fits <a href="/blog/2021/12/23/the-open-home/">our Open Home vision</a>. In the future, Matter will give us all fast, reliable, and local control of our smart home devices. At the same time, we’re realistic; this perfect vision of Matter has yet to arrive, and not everything we hoped for is possible today. Still, significant companies and organizations around the globe have committed to Matter, and they are improving it every month. We believe Matter is here to stay.</p>
<p>So, instead of discussing what isn’t currently working in Matter, we want to explain what Matter <em>can</em> offer you today. We want to show you the potential Matter has for the future and how your first steps with Matter today prepare you for that. Talk about what Thread is, how it relates to Matter - it is not the same! - and how to build your Thread network. And much more.</p>
<p>On Wednesday, January 10, at 12:00 PST / 21:00 CET, we’ll be hosting a State of Matter livestream to discuss this and address your questions and concerns about Matter and Home Assistant. We’ll make sure it’s an excellent watch for both beginners and more technically-oriented viewers - our Matter developers will be there to give you a technical deep-dive into Matter, too. Please save the date in your calendar and post all your questions and concerns in our comments section!</p>
<p><lite-youtube videoid="rEugjMk-4II" videotitle="The State of Matter"></lite-youtube></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Nabu Casa at the Matter Member Meeting]]></title>
    <link href="https://ivangrod.github.io/blog/2023/12/04/nabu-casa-at-the-matter-member-meeting/"/>
    <updated>2023-12-04T00:00:02+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://ivangrod.github.io/blog/2023/12/04/nabu-casa-at-the-matter-member-meeting</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>TL;DR: We represented Home Assistant, our community, and the Open Home vision at the Matter member meeting in Geneva. We’re hosting a live stream to talk Matter in January to update you about our progress and answer your questions. Leave your questions in the comments below!</p>
<p>Two weeks ago me, Marcel van der Veldt, and Stefan Agner, traveled to Geneva to represent Home Assistant, our community and the Open Home Vision at the Member Meeting of the Connectivity Standards Alliance (CSA). This is an important meeting where companies from all over the world meet to talk and decide about the Matter standard and how to implement it.</p>
<p><em>(Matter is the new smart home standard that promises to make everyone’s smart home devices work with each other across platforms and ecosystems, locally and privately. It’s being developed by the CSA, which is also responsible for Zigbee).</em></p>
<p class='img'>
<img src="/needlehack-blog/images/blog/2023-11-matter-member-meeting/matter-image.jpg">
Stefan and Marcel
</p>
<p>We were able to attend because <a href="https://www.nabucasa.com">Nabu Casa</a> is a member of the CSA. We pay for this with the revenue from your Home Assistant Cloud subscriptions (thank you!). CSA membership ensures that we have access to official technical documentation and support to build Matter into Home Assistant. It also gives us a voice inside the CSA, which we use to advocate for the interests of Home Assistant users and our Open Home vision.</p>
<!--more-->
<p>We love to attend these events and hear amazing stories from the people we meet. When talking with engineers working on Matter in the CSA, we noticed a lot of them run Home Assistant at their own homes and are enthusiastic supporters of the project! Talking to device manufacturers made us realize that Home Assistant is used as a test platform because our Matter server is the most flexible. This is great because it increases the likelihood that Matter devices work great in Home Assistant, as devices will have been implemented and tested on it!</p>
<p>Our participation in the development of Matter also means we’re in touch with engineers at other companies on a regular basis. One of the most popular Matter devices on the market right now, the Eve Energy Plug, has custom support for energy metering - a function not yet supported in the current Matter standard. The only way to see your energy usage was inside Eve’s own app. We’ve worked together with Eve, so we can now read the measurements from their plugs via custom Matter clusters and show them in Home Assistant! This feature will be available in the December release of Home Assistant. If you own Eve Energy Plugs, this is our early Christmas present for you.</p>
<h2>Home Assistant and Matter</h2>
<p>We haven’t just joined the CSA; we also have dedicated developers working on making sure that Matter is a first-class citizen within Home Assistant. In our eyes, it’s ideal for Home Assistant users because of the local nature of the protocol. It is our goal to make Home Assistant an officially certified Matter controller registered with the CSA.</p>
<p>To talk more about our ongoing progress with Matter, we’ll host a live stream in January. It will contain a full update on the state of Matter and go in-depth about what we have planned. We’ll announce the date soon.</p>
<p>We don’t want it to be just a stream of us talking Matter to you. We know you have many questions about Matter, things that are unclear, or that you want our help to understand. So please send us your burning questions in the comments below!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
