<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Public-Service-Announcement | Home Assistant]]></title>
  <link href="https://ivangrod.github.io/blog/categories/public-service-announcement/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://ivangrod.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2025-09-23T17:48:58+00:00</updated>
  <id>https://ivangrod.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Home Assistant]]></name>
    
  </author>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Deprecating Core and Supervised installation methods, and 32-bit systems]]></title>
    <link href="https://ivangrod.github.io/blog/2025/05/22/deprecating-core-and-supervised-installation-methods-and-32-bit-systems/"/>
    <updated>2025-05-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://ivangrod.github.io/blog/2025/05/22/deprecating-core-and-supervised-installation-methods-and-32-bit-systems</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<img src='/images/blog/2025-05-deprecation/art.png' style='border: 0;box-shadow: none;' alt="Deprecating Core and Supervised installation methods, and 32-bit systems">
<p>We are today officially deprecating two installation methods and three legacy CPU architectures. We always strive to have Home Assistant run on almost anything, but sometimes we must make difficult decisions to keep the project moving forward. Though these changes will only affect a small percentage of Home Assistant users, we want to do everything in our power to make this easy for those who may need to migrate.</p>
<p>Beginning with Home Assistant 2025.6, affected systems will display a notification after updating, indicating that <strong>support will end in six months (with release 2025.12)</strong> and include a recommendation to <a href="#how-to-migrate">migrate to a supported system</a>. In this post, we’ll go into our thinking on these deprecations and our findings after consulting the community on these changes.</p>
<p>We have deprecated the following installation methods:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Home Assistant Core</strong> installation method, where you run your system in a Python environment, not to be confused with Container (for example, running your system in Docker).</li>
<li><strong>Home Assistant’s Supervised</strong> installation method, which involves running your own operating system, then installing the Supervisor and other requirements on top of that.</li>
</ul>
<p>These are advanced installation methods, with only a small percentage of the community opting to use them. If you are using these methods, you can continue to do so (you can even continue to update your system), but in six months time, you will no longer be supported, which I’ll explain the impacts of in the next section. References to these installation methods will be removed from our documentation after our next release (2025.6). Going forward <a href="https://github.com/home-assistant/operating-system">Home Assistant OS</a> and <a href="https://hub.docker.com/r/homeassistant/home-assistant">Home Assistant Container</a> will become the only supported installation methods.</p>
<p>In the future, only the currently supported 64-bit architectures (aarch64 and amd64) will be used. The following legacy architectures are being deprecated:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>i386</strong> (32-bit x86) is an architecture used by Intel and AMD predominantly before 2003, but some later processors still utilized it (e.g., early Intel Atom models).</li>
<li><strong>armhf</strong> (32-bit ARM hard-float) was used by very early single-board computers, notably the original Raspberry Pi.</li>
<li><strong>armv7</strong> (32-bit ARM) was used by a number of early single-board computers, most notably the Raspberry Pi 2.</li>
</ul>
<p>If you are one of the few with a system using these architectures, you will receive a notification after updating to 2025.6, and it will describe how to migrate your system. In six months, your system will become unsupported and will no longer receive updates.</p>
<p><a href="#check-if-youre-affected">Check our guide to see if your current Home Assistant installation is affected.</a><!--more--></p>
<h2>What does deprecated and unsupported mean</h2>
<p>In the simplest terms, deprecation is where you stop recommending a certain feature to users as you intend to remove it soon. As we deprecated the Core and Supervised installations methods today, that means we are now working to remove all references to them from our documentation. The goal is to guide new users towards installation methods we plan to support long term, and discourage the use of those that are being phased out.</p>
<p>Even though they are being deprecated, we are committing to support them for a further six months (until release 2025.12), giving existing users time to migrate to Home Assistant OS or Container. During this time we will ensure these installation types keep functioning as normal during the deprecation period. However, after those six months have elapsed, these methods will become unsupported, which means issue reports will no longer be accepted. As these installation methods are used for the development of Home Assistant, it will still be technically possible to update them. We still would recommend migrating to a supported method, but that’s your choice.</p>
<p>As i386, armhf, and armv7 architectures have also been deprecated, we are currently removing references to them from our documentation. More importantly, they will also be subject to a six-month support window. After that support ends (from release 2025.12 onwards), we will no longer build or release distributions or containers targeting these platforms. This will mean that in six months’ time, there will be no more updates for these systems, and if users encounter issues, they will no longer be able to ask for support from Home Assistant maintainers.</p>
<h2>Why we made this decision</h2>
<h3>Core and Supervised</h3>
<p class='img'><img src='/images/blog/2025-05-deprecation/analytics.png' alt="OS and Container represent the vast majority of installation methods">From our <a href="https://analytics.home-assistant.io/">opt-in analytics</a></p>
<p>The Core and Supervised installation methods are not only complex for users to install and maintain — they’re also challenging for the Home Assistant team to support. In the past, there were compelling reasons, outside Home Assistant development, to run these installation methods, but for most people those reasons are disappearing. Home Assistant OS is very capable with a rich ecosystem of add-ons, while also being easy to run in a virtual machine. Container adoption has become mainstream, now being widely available along with systems having more resources to run them. Steadily, we’ve seen year-on-year reductions in the percentage of Core and Supervised installations (currently standing at 2.5% and 3.3% respectively).</p>
<p>As Core and Supervised are more complex to maintain, they generate more issues that are more difficult to solve. This complexity places a disproportionate burden on our community-driven support system, where volunteers generously give their time to help others. It also takes time away from assisting the vast majority of users who are on the simpler to maintain installation methods. Along with this, new users could sometimes be swayed into running Core or Supervised, and have a bad experience that could cause them to give up on the best way to automate their home. By focusing our support and documentation on OS and Container methods, we can greatly improve the onboarding experience and ensure a smoother start for new users.</p>
<h3>Legacy 32-bit architectures</h3>
<p>Though Home Assistant is very lean and can run great on older or low-spec hardware, the architectures we’re deprecating are definitely on the leaner side of the spectrum. That probably explains why we see such low usage figures, with i386 and armhf architectures representing less than 0.5% of installations each, and armv7 at only 0.95% of installations. More than half of Home Assistant systems using armv7 have hardware that is capable of running 64-bit operating systems, like Raspberry Pi 3 and 4. This hardware can actually upgrade and migrate to a supported 64-bit version of our Home Assistant Operating System</p>
<p>The broader software and hardware industries have also shifted away from these older 32-bit systems. Most have adopted 64-bit architectures such as amd64 and aarch64, and we are seeing more projects we depend on no longer supporting these 32-bit architectures. There have already been several instances where keeping support for these architectures has held back the development of new features.</p>
<h2>Your feedback</h2>
<p>For any major change, it is our goal to make sure the community guides this decision-making. When our maintainers initially proposed these deprecations, we shared this plan with the community (in our forum, GitHub, Discord, Reddit, and other social channels), using it to gather feedback. It was a constructive, civil discussion, and we learned a couple of interesting things that have helped us move this decision forward.</p>
<p>First, our current wording is confusing to the community. Core and Supervisor are components of Home Assistant OS, but are also similar—or the same—as the names of installation methods, which is not super clear for new users. We also found these installation methods being used in ways we never expected, and there are a good number of people who were already running Home Assistant in custom and unsupported ways, not even realizing they were unsupported.</p>
<p>Many of those impacted asked for better guidance on how to migrate. A good number were unaware of our expansion of backup and restore features to all installation methods, significantly smoothing their transition to a new platform.</p>
<h2>Check if you’re affected</h2>
<p class='img'><img src='/images/blog/2025-05-deprecation/system-information.png' alt="what the system information dialog looks like">The blue arrow shows your installation type, and the red arrow displays the architecture.</p>
<p>If you are unsure which <strong>installation method</strong> you are running:</p>
<ul>
<li>Select <a href="https://my.home-assistant.io/redirect/system_health/">this link</a> OR Navigate to <em><strong>Settings &gt; System &gt; Repairs</strong></em>, select the three-dotted menu in the top right corner, and select <em><strong>System information</strong></em>.</li>
<li>Check the Installation type field. If you are running Home Assistant OS, or Container, you are fine as the installation method deprecation doesn’t apply to you.</li>
</ul>
<p>In this <a href="https://my.home-assistant.io/redirect/system_health/">same window</a>, you can find the <strong>architecture</strong> as well:</p>
<ul>
<li>The CPU architecture field will tell you exactly which architecture you are using. If you are seeing aarch64 or x86_64 here, you are fine as the architecture deprecation doesn’t apply to you.</li>
</ul>
<h2>How to migrate</h2>
<p class='img'><img src='/images/blog/2025-05-deprecation/methods.png' alt="Installation methods and their functionality">Green are staying, and red are deprecated.</p>
<p>If it’s been a while since you’ve migrated Home Assistant systems, a lot has improved over the past several years. Switching systems is as easy as <a href="/common-tasks/general/#backups">making a backup</a>, downloading it, and <a href="/common-tasks/general/#restoring-a-backup">restoring</a> it during the initialization of your new system (Home Assistant Cloud subscribers using off-site backups can restore <a href="/blog/2025/04/02/release-20254/#onboarding-with-a-home-assistant-cloud-backup">with just their password</a>). Every Home Assistant installation method now has backups, and you can restore backups from any method onto another regardless of the differences in architecture. In many cases, very little needs to be done once the restore is successful (<a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/homeassistant/comments/1kdip17/are_you_kidding_me/">to the dismay of tinkerers online</a>). Our documentation has a full list of guides on <a href="/installation/">how to install Home Assistant on different hardware</a>.</p>
<p>Before you think about migrating to a different installation method, you can always choose to stick with what you have. Just because it becomes unsupported by the Home Assistant project, it doesn’t mean you can’t keep running it like you do today. That choice is up to you.</p>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Need</th>
<th>Currently using</th>
<th>Migrate to</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Home Assistant with add-ons</td>
<td>Supervised</td>
<td>Home Assistant OS</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>A system without Home Assistant OS support</td>
<td>Supervised</td>
<td>Container (many add-ons can be run as containers alongside Home Assistant)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Full control of the host system</td>
<td>Supervised</td>
<td>Run Home Assistant OS in a VM, or Container (alongside add-on containers)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Lightweight solution</td>
<td>Core</td>
<td>Container</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>For <strong>Home Assistant Core</strong> users, the closest alternative is Home Assistant Container, which is most commonly used with Docker. If you can dedicate a device exclusively to Home Assistant, the recommended installation method is Home Assistant OS, which gives an appliance-like setup.</p>
<p>For <strong>Home Assistant Supervised</strong> users, we recommend migrating to Home Assistant OS—it supports everything Supervised does, including add-ons. If you want more control over the OS, you can also run Home Assistant OS in a virtual machine, like with Proxmox, or go the Home Assistant Container path alternatively.</p>
<p>For <strong>deprecated architectures</strong>, there is generally no supported migration path using your existing hardware. You will therefore need to find alternative hardware compatible with Home Assistant OS or Container. Second-hand single-board computers and recycled small-form-factor office machines are affordable and sustainable options. In some cases, your system may be running a 32-bit operating system, but is capable of running a 64-bit one (Raspberry Pi 3 and 4 are examples of systems often running a 32-bit OS despite being capable of running 64-bit). In this case, you will need to install a 64-bit capable operating system and restore Home Assistant on that system.</p>
<h2>Frequently asked questions</h2>
<ul>
<li>
<p><em><strong>If Home Assistant Core is used for development, and part of the developer docs, why not just offer it to end-users?</strong></em><br />
This is not just about technical viability, it is also about helping and supporting people with their issues, problems, and questions, in our forums and chat. Having these options available to less technical people leads to support queries, and if they have a bad first experience that reflects poorly on the project. Users are free to continue running their systems the way they would like.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><em><strong>No support for Core or Supervised—can I still use them?</strong></em><br />
You can still use them even if we no longer support them. There are many users running Home Assistant in all kinds of unofficial ways. This change just means we are removing it from our end-user documentation and will no longer recommend using these installation methods from an official standpoint.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><em><strong>Will the developer documentation on these things remain?</strong></em><br />
Yes, those will remain. The developer documentation for running Home Assistant’s Core Python application directly in a Python virtual environment will remain. This is how we develop. This proposal is about removing end-user documentation and support.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><em><strong>Can I start maintaining these installation methods?</strong></em><br />
While maintaining these methods will require effort, the community is free to move documentation and code to new independent projects. Our maintainers will no longer accept issues or provide end-user documentation, but that shouldn’t stop anyone passionate about them from continuing to run them, or helping others to do the same.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><em><strong>Can I reproduce any of the installations you offer?</strong></em><br />
Yes, of course! All our pipelines are open source and transparent, you can always recreate any of our pipelines and release artifacts; either automated or manual.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><em><strong>Is this the first step towards making Home Assistant closed source/proprietary/commercial?</strong></em><br />
No, that is impossible. Home Assistant will always remain open source. Home Assistant is owned by the <a href="https://www.openhomefoundation.org/">Open Home Foundation</a>, a Swiss non-profit foundation that is audited and governed, and—by law—bound by its mission. This means it will always be open source and cannot be bought or sold.</p>
</li>
</ul>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Home Assistant Connect ZBT-1 issue and replacement]]></title>
    <link href="https://ivangrod.github.io/blog/2024/10/02/connect-zbt1-issue-and-replacement/"/>
    <updated>2024-10-02T00:01:01+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://ivangrod.github.io/blog/2024/10/02/connect-zbt1-issue-and-replacement</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<img src='/images/blog/2024-10-zbt1-issue/art.jpg' alt="Home Assistant Connect ZBT-1 issue and replacement">
<div class="alert alert-note">
  <p class="alert-title"><iconify-icon inline icon='mdi:information-outline'></iconify-icon> Note</p>
  <div class="alert-content">
<p>The replacement program is now operational, please contact the retailer where you purchased your device to request a replacement. The replacement program only covers ZBT-1 branded devices purchased prior to October 2024, and not SkyConnect-branded devices (identify which device you have <a href="#do-i-have-a-zbt-1">with this graphic</a>).</p>
  </div>
</div>
<p>We’ve found an issue in Home Assistant Connect ZBT-1 that has affected a small number of customers, which appears to be the result of a faulty part incorporated in the first production run of ZBT-1 devices, causing the device to fail and become completely unresponsive. We want to make sure everyone can get a replacement ZBT-1 and ensure they are covered far into the future.</p>
<p>Though Home Assistant SkyConnect is identical to the ZBT-1 under the hood, <strong>it is not affected</strong>. The design is not what’s at fault, but instead, a defective voltage regulator that was used in this specific production run that is causing the issue. When a ZBT-1 is inserted into certain USB-A ports, the voltage regulator can fail, fully bricking the device. We used high-quality manufacturing and quality control in this and previous production runs. We are undertaking an investigation to find out how this could happen and most importantly, to avoid a repeat of anything remotely similar in the future.</p>
<p>We’re sorry for any inconvenience this may cause you. Below are details on our investigation, how devices are affected, and the replacement program.</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="#background">Background</a></li>
<li><a href="#do-i-have-a-zbt-1">Do I have a ZBT-1?</a></li>
<li><a href="#pausing-sales">Pausing sales</a></li>
<li><a href="#replacement-program">Replacement Program</a></li>
<li><a href="#conclusion">Conclusion</a></li>
</ul>
<!--more-->
<h2>Background</h2>
<p>Around a month ago, we were contacted about one of our latest (and <a href="/blog/2024/06/13/zbt1-annoucement/">recently rebranded</a>) Home Assistant Connect ZBT-1s not being detected and showing a deformation on the housing. A couple more similar issues were reported, and we began a dialogue with the small number of people who were affected, having them send us the devices to test.</p>
<p class='img'><img src='/images/blog/2024-10-zbt1-issue/zbt1-issue.jpg' style='border: 0;box-shadow: none;' alt="ZBT-1 case deformation and faulty voltage regulator">Circled in red the deformation on the case and the board showing the failed chip</p>
<p>Indeed, the device no longer worked at all, not being detected by any device it was connected to. When we opened them, we found a dead voltage regulator. Though SkyConnect devices can also develop a small discoloration on the outside casing after long-term use, and this is not a sign of failure, the deeper deformation in the outer casing pictured above is a sign that the ZBT-1 has overheated and failed. All of our devices are certified by CE and ROHS, and the plastic shell has been designed not to combust. This is a real-life demonstration of just how important this certification is and why we take that step.</p>
<p>We replaced the voltage regulator on the devices we tested, and the devices sprang back to life. We found our culprit, but why was it failing? As mentioned, the SkyConnect internal design and the manufacturing were effectively identical to the ZBT-1, and we received no reports of any such failures in the literally tens of thousands of them in the wild. In manufacturing runs there is always a little variance, and in this run, something went wrong with the voltage regulator that was sourced - again, we’re looking into this.</p>
<p>It took us a couple of weeks to replicate the problem with our own units. We went down some wrong paths, but eventually found it was triggered only by certain devices, specifically certain desktop PCs (internally, we have only found one desktop that causes this failure). We have not observed the failure occur when the device has only been connected to a Home Assistant Green, Raspberry Pi, or even a Mac. If you have plugged your ZBT-1 into a different device, specifically a desktop PC, and it is not recognized by that system, inspect it for this deformation pictured above. Obviously, we want you to be able to use the device with any hardware, and even if only a small number of devices from this production run have reported issues, it is still unacceptable to us.</p>
<h2>Do I have a ZBT-1?</h2>
<img src='/images/blog/2024-10-zbt1-issue/skyconnect-zbt1.png' style='border: 0;box-shadow: none;' alt="SkyConnect (left) and ZBT-1 (right)">
<p style="text-align: center; font-size: 0.9rem;">SkyConnect (left) and ZBT-1 (right) branded devices, SkyConnect are unaffected by this issue.</p>
<h2>Pausing sales</h2>
<p>We have asked our distributors to pause sales and return all stock. For the next month, you will see “Out of Stock” banners, and if you are attempting to get a replacement device for a failed unit, this will not be possible until production is resumed.</p>
<p>We are working to have replacement ZBT-1s shipped by early November.</p>
<h2>Replacement Program</h2>
<p>If you have purchased Home Assistant Connect ZBT-1, we are working on a replacement program. This program will see Nabu Casa provide a replacement device free of charge for a period of 60 months (5 years) for verified purchases. Regardless of whether the device has failed, we will provide a replacement upon request.</p>
<p>It is a core value of ours to do things as sustainably as possible, and that’s why we’ve provided such a long coverage period. We want to give owners with working ZBT-1s, who do not expect to use the device in a different system for the foreseeable future, the ability to keep it operating with peace of mind.</p>
<div class="alert alert-note">
  <p class="alert-title"><iconify-icon inline icon='mdi:information-outline'></iconify-icon> Note</p>
  <div class="alert-content">
<p>All ZBT-1 branded devices produced, as of October 2024, are believed to have this fault. You can tell if your device is a ZBT-1 by checking the white label on the back for “ZBT-1” (identify which device you have <a href="#do-i-have-a-zbt-1">with this graphic</a>). There is no need to test if your device is affected by this fault.</p>
  </div>
</div>
<p>If it’s working, keep it plugged into the device it’s working with, and don’t worry about a replacement until you need it. If you need or want a replacement, please contact the seller where you purchased your device, and they will arrange the return process and replacement. Replacement devices are expected by early November, and we will be prioritizing people with non-functioning devices.</p>
<h2>Conclusion</h2>
<p>We’re sorry for the inconvenience and any disruption to your smart home. As someone who uses Zigbee in their home, which many smart devices rely on, I would hate to have it out of commission.</p>
<p>Worse things can happen, but this has been a gut punch. All our work at Nabu Casa is to fund the development of Home Assistant and support the Open Home. Issues like this eat into our time, and rob our users of new and great things. Ultimately, we’re going to take this setback as a chance to prove we stand by our values and do the right thing.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Disabling new login page functionality]]></title>
    <link href="https://ivangrod.github.io/blog/2023/12/14/disabling-new-login-page-functionality/"/>
    <updated>2023-12-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://ivangrod.github.io/blog/2023/12/14/disabling new login page functionality</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In <a href="https://www.home-assistant.io/blog/2023/12/06/release-202312/">release 2023.12</a> we added a redesigned login page to Home Assistant. It detects when you are accessing Home Assistant via your local home network, and if so, presents a redesigned login experience that shows your user profiles. If you access Home Assistant from outside your home network, the login page still asks for your username and password, like before.</p>
<p>We have heard the concerns from the community that this functionality can open up your Home Assistant instance to a user enumeration attack from within the local network. A malicious actor with access to your local network could get the names and pictures of all Home Assistant users. They could use this information to make attacking your Home Assistant instance easier.</p>
<p>A security issue was filed for this on December 10, we have accepted and published the corresponding <a href="https://github.com/home-assistant/core/security/advisories/GHSA-jqpc-rc7g-vf83">GitHub Security Advisory</a>, and have disabled the redesigned login page functionality in patch 2023.12.3 released on December 14.</p>
<p>While researching the feedback we received, we were troubled to discover that the users who experienced problems with the new login page often used misconfigured reverse proxies. When the reverse proxy is not configured correctly, Home Assistant is no longer able to discern between traffic from your local home network or a public network. These users would see the redesigned login page when accessing Home Assistant from outside their home network.</p>
<p>To improve the network security of these users, we are researching how we can use Home Assistant to detect more variations of misconfigured proxies and inform them about it.</p>
<p>We redesigned the login page because we believed the local home network is within the privacy of your own home and a trusted environment for showing the people in it. We assumed that users attempting to log in on the local network are also trusted and allowed to see other user profiles, similar to what Microsoft, Apple, Netflix, and other companies assume in their products.</p>
<p>That said, we do hear you and take your feedback, and the potential security risk to users with misconfigured reverse proxies, seriously. Thank you for bringing this to our attention and being open about your concerns.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Removal of MyQ integration]]></title>
    <link href="https://ivangrod.github.io/blog/2023/11/06/removal-of-myq-integration/"/>
    <updated>2023-11-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://ivangrod.github.io/blog/2023/11/06/removal-of-myq-integration</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>TL;DR:</strong> The MyQ integration will be removed from Home Assistant in release 2023.12 on December 6, 2023. Chamberlain Group, the owners of MyQ, have released a public statement saying they will continue blocking access to third-party apps, like the MyQ integration. For current MyQ users we recommend <a href="https://paulwieland.github.io/ratgdo/">ratgdo</a>, a device that physically connects to your MyQ garage door opener and allows you to control it locally.</p>
<p>If you own a garage door opener from Chamberlain or Liftmaster, you are probably familiar with MyQ. It’s a cloud-based smart home brand owned by Chamberlain Group, best known for its smart garage devices. MyQ is also currently one of the most problematic integrations for Home Assistant users. The MyQ garage door opener integration has, for the past months, been in a state of <a href="https://community.home-assistant.io/t/the-current-state-of-myq-from-the-codeowner/630623">constant repair</a> as the integration breaks, is fixed, and then breaks again. This is a direct result of actions taken by MyQ to block access from third parties.</p>
<!--more-->
<p>Last month, Chamberlain Group put out a <a href="https://chamberlaingroup.com/press/a-message-about-our-decision-to-prevent-unauthorized-usage-of-myq">statement</a> by their CTO, Dan Phillips, on this matter:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Chamberlain Group recently made the decision to prevent unauthorized usage of our myQ ecosystem through third-party apps. This decision was made so that we can continue to provide the best possible experience for our 10 million+ users, as well as our authorized partners who put their trust in us. We understand that this impacts a small percentage of users, but ultimately this will improve the performance and reliability of myQ, benefiting all of our users.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This <em>‘unauthorized usage’</em> appears to refer to the MyQ integration for Home Assistant which was added to Home Assistant in February, 2017. We have reached out to Chamberlain Group in several ways to see if we can come to an understanding, but we have not received an official response. We can only assume that this means Chamberlain Group has made its decision and will force customers to use only the MyQ app or those of their authorized partners.</p>
<p>You may wonder if Home Assistant could become an authorized partner. In their partner program, the partner companies pay Chamberlain Group for the privilege of letting MyQ owners control their own garage doors. We are open to working together with Chamberlain Group, but as Home Assistant is an open-source project, we cannot pay a partnership fee. Not only is this financially not viable, it also goes against our values. MyQ users should be able to access the devices they paid for and the data they own in any way they want, without a third party having to pay an additional fee.</p>
<p>So, to quote the maintainer of the MyQ integration, <a href="https://github.com/Lash-L">Lash-L</a>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>We are playing a game of cat and mouse with MyQ and right now it looks like the cat is winning.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Once a company decides to be hostile to its customers, the only way we can win is by not playing their game at all. Do not buy products or services from companies that treat their customers this way. Tell your friends not to deal with companies that treat their customers this way. Buy products that work locally and won’t stop functioning when management wants an additional revenue stream.</p>
<p>Because we cannot continue to work around Chamberlain Group if they keep blocking access to third parties, the MyQ integration will be removed from Home Assistant in the upcoming 2023.12 release on December 6, 2023. We are very disappointed that it has come to this and sincerely hope that Chamberlain Group is willing to reconsider its position. We would happily welcome this integration back if Chamberlain Group would work with us for the good of their customers.</p>
<p>For now, if you are a MyQ owner, we’re afraid you are in the ‘small percentage of users’ Chamberlain Group refuses to serve. We recommend buying <a href="https://paulwieland.github.io/ratgdo/">ratgdo</a>.</p>
<p>Ratgdo is a fully local, ESPHome-based, solution that is compatible with MyQ’s security+ protocol and can be installed on an existing MyQ system by connecting three wires. It offers the same garage door controls that MyQ does and even adds features that MyQ does not have, like motion events, controlling the light, and locking out wired remotes.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Removal of Mazda Connected Services integration]]></title>
    <link href="https://ivangrod.github.io/blog/2023/10/13/removal-of-mazda-connected-services-integration/"/>
    <updated>2023-10-13T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://ivangrod.github.io/blog/2023/10/13/removal-of-mazda-connected-services-integration</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>On October 11, 2023, we were informed that an open-source contributor received a cease and desist letter from Mazda North American Operations (Mazda) regarding his library to connect with Mazda services. This library was used by the Home Assistant integration Mazda Connected Services, which he also maintained. A <a href="https://github.com/github/dmca/blob/master/2023/10/2023-10-10-mazda.md">DMCA notice</a> was sent to GitHub requesting the removal of all code and forked repositories as well.</p>
<p>The contributor has complied with the cease and desist letter. The library is no longer available, and the Mazda Connected Services integration has been removed from Home Assistant in the 2023.10.2 patch release of Home Assistant released on October 12, 2023.</p>
<p>Home Assistant is disappointed that Mazda has decided to take this position. We’re also sad that Mazda’s first recourse was not to reach out to us and the maintainer but to send a cease and desist letter instead.</p>
<p>We invite Mazda to speak with us about this topic. We would love to have an open and constructive discussion about the potential that a Home Assistant integration has for them and their customers. We genuinely believe there is a common ground between us and Mazda when it comes to enabling the owners of their cars to explore the possibilities of their own data.</p>
<p>After all, other car manufacturers do see this potential. For example, Tesla has recently released <a href="https://developer.tesla.com/docs/fleet-api">official API documentation</a> to support third-party apps. Volkswagen Group’s Audi brand has <a href="https://cariad.technology/de/en/news/stories/launch-application-store-for-volkswagen-group.html">launched an app store in their cars</a> that features the Home Assistant app. We hope Mazda will see this potential, as well.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
