<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Z-Wave | Home Assistant]]></title>
  <link href="https://ivangrod.github.io/blog/categories/z-wave/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://ivangrod.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2025-09-23T17:42:31+00:00</updated>
  <id>https://ivangrod.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Home Assistant]]></name>
    
  </author>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Z-Wave reborn - Home Assistant Connect ZWA-2]]></title>
    <link href="https://ivangrod.github.io/blog/2025/08/13/home-assistant-connect-zwa-2/"/>
    <updated>2025-08-13T00:00:01+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://ivangrod.github.io/blog/2025/08/13/home-assistant-connect-zwa-2</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<img src='/images/blog/2025-08-home-assistant-connect-zwa-2/art.webp' style='border: 0;box-shadow: none;' alt="Z-Wave reborn - Home Assistant Connect ZWA-2">
<p>Introducing the <a href="/connect/zwa-2/">Home Assistant Connect ZWA-2</a>, the ultimate way to connect Z-Wave devices to Home Assistant. Between its optimized antenna and seamless integration with Home Assistant, it should be a big upgrade for anyone using Z-Wave today.</p>
<p>If you’re not using Z-Wave, it’s time to take a second look, as Connect ZWA-2 is a different beast. It might be just what you need to reach that tricky spot in your home… or even beyond. Connect ZWA-2 supports Z-Wave Long Range, and this modern take on the standard delivers exceptional reach along with more responsive, battery-efficient devices. Every home is different, but our testers have managed connections in places they once thought impossible.</p>
<p>Join the smart home range revolution for <strong>$69 or €59</strong> (that’s the recommended MSRP, and pricing will vary by retailer). For quick details, specs, and where to buy, visit our <a href="/connect/zwa-2/">Home Assistant Connect ZWA-2 page</a>. It’s available for purchase today. Read on to learn what goes into the ultimate Z-Wave upgrade.</p>
<p><a href="/needlehack-blog/connect/zwa-2" style="display:block;text-align:center;"><img src='/images/blog/2025-08-home-assistant-connect-zwa-2/buy.webp' style='border: 0;box-shadow: none;' alt="Buy the Home Assistant Connect ZWA-2"></a></p>
<!--more-->
<h2>We love open standards</h2>
<p>Open standards let you connect devices directly to Home Assistant for local, private control, and keep working for years, even if the manufacturer disappears. To make connecting these standards as seamless as possible, we like to build our own hardware.</p>
<p>In late 2022, we launched <a href="/connectzbt1/">Home Assistant Connect ZBT-1</a> (formerly SkyConnect), a USB adapter for Zigbee and Thread. It made both protocols much easier to get started with, and sales helped fund Home Assistant development. We knew the next standard to tackle was Z-Wave, and after another couple of hardware launches (<a href="/green">Home Assistant Green</a> and <a href="/voice-pe/">Voice Preview Edition</a>), we finally had the time to do it right.</p>
<h3>Why Z-Wave?</h3>
<p>If you’re new to Z-Wave, its key advantage over other open standards is its use of sub-GHz radio waves, which are better at getting through thick walls and reaching across large households. While Wi-Fi, Bluetooth, Zigbee, and Thread all compete for the same crowded airspace (2.4 GHz), Z-Wave operates in its own much quieter spectrum (865-926 MHz). Z-Wave is great for range, but its new <a href="https://z-wavealliance.org/what-is-z-wave-long-range-how-does-it-differ-from-z-wave/">Z-Wave Long Range variant</a> builds even further on this… <em>but more on that later</em>.</p>
<p>As the standard is over two decades old, it’s had a lot of time to iron out any kinks, but it also has over 4,500 certified devices to choose from. Our opt-in stats show over 130,000 Home Assistant households are using Z-Wave today. Several <a href="https://works-with.home-assistant.io/">Works with Home Assistant</a> partners are building amazing Z-Wave products, including <a href="/integrations/zooz/">Zooz</a>, <a href="/integrations/shelly_zwave/">Shelly</a>, <a href="/integrations/ultraloq/">Ultraloq</a>, <a href="/integrations/leviton_z_wave/">Leviton</a>, and <a href="/integrations/homeseer/">Homeseer</a>. You can also go to any local marketplace and pick up any working Z-Wave smart device, no matter how old, and it will still connect with Home Assistant!</p>
<h2>Connect ZWA-2 in-depth</h2>
<p>We’ve learned a lot about hardware since the launch of Connect ZBT-1, and we also knew we could breathe some new life into Z-Wave on Home Assistant. Making this device was the start of us leveling up the Connect platform and establishing our <strong>second generation</strong>, which is all about building the most performant and open design. That is why we jumped straight to <em>two</em> for this Connect ZWA-2!</p>
<h3>Go big or go home</h3>
<p>To be the most performant, we knew we had to ditch the “stick” form factor. It was never ideal, as USB ports can output a lot of interference. We even shipped a USB extender with Connect ZBT-1, and urged people to use it, as it kept the device away from any noisy components. Instead of building a stick we built an <em>adapter</em>, which includes an optimized standalone antenna and base that connects to your Home Assistant system with a USB cable.</p>
<img src='/images/blog/2025-08-home-assistant-connect-zwa-2/precisely-engineered.webp' style='border: 0;box-shadow: none;' alt="Comparison of the Home Assistant Connect ZWA-2 antenna to other Z-Wave antennas, showing the size difference">
<p>We’re not compensating for anything; a big antenna does make a big difference. For starters, you need an antenna that’s the right size for your wavelength. As Z-Wave is in the sub-GHz, this means the antenna has to be longer than your average Wi-Fi antenna (about 33 cm or a foot is the sweet spot).</p>
<p>You need to optimize not just the antenna, but also the base of the device (also known as the <em>ground plane</em>). Our hardware experts really went deep into all the physics involved, and the results speak for themselves. Basically, by choosing the right ratio of antenna to base, the two work in harmony to maximize the range and reliability of the signal.</p>
<p>While some Z-Wave adapters may claim they can hit the maximum transmit levels with their postage-stamp-sized antennas, that can sometimes come with a lot of interference. We’ve engineered away that problem. Connect ZWA-2 can speak loudly and clearly 🗣️, and what’s even more important, it’s a great listener 👂.</p>
<h3>Positioning is everything</h3>
<p>Having a big optimized antenna is great, but placement is almost as important. Its sturdy base and good-sized USB cable allow it to be placed in the right spot. No more will you have a dangling dongle hidden behind a server cabinet. We even put in an accelerometer to ensure people position the antenna upright, this ensures devices are in the sweet spot of the antenna. If you place it on its side, it will subtly blink the status light at the top.</p>
<h3>All the Z-Wave</h3>
<p>Inside Connect ZWA-2, we include the latest Z-Wave 800 chip, which supports all Z-Wave devices. We’re also Z-Wave certified, giving you that extra peace of mind. This, combined with Home Assistant’s industry-leading Z-Wave software, means Z-Wave has never been this good. On your certified smart devices, you might see Security 2 (S2), SmartStart, Z-Wave Plus, or Z-Wave Plus V2 — don’t worry, we support it all. One new feature we support that is getting people very excited is Z-Wave Long Range👇.</p>
<h3>Go long</h3>
<img src='/images/blog/2025-08-home-assistant-connect-zwa-2/supports-all-devices.webp' style='border: 0;box-shadow: none;' alt="Isometric view of the Home Assistant Connect ZWA-2 revealing the internal PCB featuring the Z-Wave 800 chipset">
<p>Combining Z-Wave’s natural abilities with an optimized antenna has given us some impressive range, but we took it a few steps further. We added Z-Wave Long Range to Connect ZWA-2, which might be one of the most substantial updates to Z-Wave yet.</p>
<div class="alert">
    <p><strong>Z-Wave Long Range</strong><br> Long Range doesn’t use mesh, where devices relay messages through each other to reach the hub. Instead, each device talks straight to your hub, which brings some benefits. It runs on the same frequency as regular Z-Wave but at a higher power, and uses new technology that lets it reach farther, handle more devices, respond faster, and save battery. Right now, it is only available in North America and Europe, and the selection of compatible devices is still growing. This is just scratching the surface; for more on this impressive tech, read a <a href="https://z-wavealliance.org/what-is-z-wave-long-range-how-does-it-differ-from-z-wave/" target="_blank">full breakdown</a> from our friends at the Z-Wave Alliance.</p>
</div>
<p>Z-Wave Long Range is different enough that it needs its own separate network. Connect ZWA-2 can run both Z-Wave and Z-Wave Long Range <strong>at the same time</strong>. When you add a Long Range capable device to Home Assistant, the setup wizard lets you choose which network to use. This way, you get the best of both worlds: a strong mesh network for your older devices, and the reach of Long Range for the newest devices that include support.</p>
<h3>How long?</h3>
<p class="img">
<img src='/images/blog/2025-08-home-assistant-connect-zwa-2/zwa-2-prototype-testing.webp' style='border: 0;box-shadow: none;' alt="Dominic with our stick prototype alongside DrZWave with the controller reference design. Uwe is on the other bridge, 0.7 miles away">
See that bridge in the background? Our prototype connected to a device all the way over there.
</p>
<p>People are getting some impressive results with ZWA-2:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>You might have seen our range testing <a href="/blog/2024/05/08/zwave-is-not-dead/#range-testing-our-z-wave-stick-prototype">in a previous blog</a>. Since then, we’ve optimized the design and achieved a line-of-sight range of 1.5 kilometers (0.9 miles) 🤯. This was under less than ideal circumstances (raining and within a car), and we think we could go even further.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>The certifying engineer said it was “the best range she had ever seen”.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Another test had it communicating via Z-Wave Long Range through several floors of concrete.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Testers with outdoor lights and internal brick walls have commented on how this is the first time they’ve had reliable connections with devices.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Interesting Long Range use cases have included smart mailboxes that notify you when <em>you’ve got mail</em>, or contact sensors on garden gates.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>Every home and setup is different, so we can’t definitively say how far your devices will span. What we can say is that nothing else we’ve tested comes close to what Connect ZWA-2 can do.</p>
<h3>Built for Home Assistant</h3>
<img src='/images/blog/2025-08-home-assistant-connect-zwa-2/plug-and-play.webp' style='border: 0;box-shadow: none;' alt="Home Assistant Connect ZWA-2 connected to a Home Assistant Green">
<p>Whenever we build new hardware, we step up our software development to match. You may have noticed a lot of love going into Z-Wave for Home Assistant. All Z-Wave users benefit from this, and when people buy Connect ZWA-2, they’re helping fund this development.</p>
<p>Connect ZWA-2 is built for Home Assistant, and because of this, it’s super easy to get started with. We’ve built Connect ZWA-2 to support every region, no matter where you buy it from. When you plug in Connect ZWA-2, it automatically detects and sets your region using the location configured in your Home Assistant system.</p>
<p>We’ve built handy wizards to help you set up your first Z-Wave network and to guide you in setting up new devices. A wizard also helps you quickly migrate from most Z-Wave adapters to Connect ZWA-2 in a couple of clicks. We also have the ability to update the firmware of Connect ZWA-2 right from Home Assistant, and update the firmware over-the-air (OTA) of Z-Wave devices in a single click.</p>
<h3>ESP inside</h3>
<p class="img">
<img src='/images/blog/2025-08-home-assistant-connect-zwa-2/zwa-2-pcb.webp' style='border: 0;box-shadow: none;' alt="Front and back of the PCB outside the shell of the Home Assistant Connect ZWA-2">
I’ll save you the time opening it up; here is the front and back of the PCB.
</p>
<p>As always, we’ve made Connect ZWA-2 easy to open. Just pop out the rubber feet and remove the four Phillips screws, with no glue or clips to get in the way. If you do open it up, you’ll see a familiar sight, an ESP32-S3. We’re using it as a USB controller, and it’s not running ESPHome. Yes, it does have a “Wi-Fi antenna”, but we’re not using it. We’ve provided a lot of easily accessible pins/pads, open source firmware files, unlocked bootloader, and good documentation, so feel free to tinker. We’ll also provide all the files to allow you to 3D-print the outer casing.</p>
<h3>Blending into the home</h3>
<img src='/images/blog/2025-08-home-assistant-connect-zwa-2/in-the-home.webp' alt="Home Assistant Connect ZWA-2 sitting on a shelf next to a plant and some books">
<p>It’s no small feat to make something 33 cm (1 ft) long look so subtle in the home. We’ve modeled its design after a candle and even used the top of the antenna as a status indicator. Its quality injection-molded exterior has a premium feel and shares many design cues from our sleek-looking Voice Preview Edition.</p>
<h2>Join the smart home range revolution</h2>
<p>Last year, we proclaimed in a blog that “<a href="/blog/2024/05/08/zwave-is-not-dead/">Z-Wave is not dead</a>”, and this hardware is a testament to that belief. Even with new technologies being released every week, there’s still room to innovate with something tried and tested. We will always support technology that respects your privacy, allows you to control your devices without the cloud, all while keeping the things you already have in your home running for years to come.</p>
<p>After 1600 words on a Z-Wave adapter, we’re obviously very proud of what we’ve built and excited to see what amazing things people will do with this labor of love. So, whether you’re a Z-Wave veteran or just interested in cool new technology, take a look at <a href="/connect/zwa-2/">Home Assistant Connect ZWA-2</a> today.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Z-Wave is not dead]]></title>
    <link href="https://ivangrod.github.io/blog/2024/05/08/zwave-is-not-dead/"/>
    <updated>2024-05-08T00:00:01+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://ivangrod.github.io/blog/2024/05/08/zwave-is-not-dead</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p class="img"><img src='/images/blog/2024-05-zwave-is-not-dead/art.jpg'/><i>Art by Clelia Rella</i></p>
<p><strong>TL;DR: Z-Wave is alive and well, partly due to a strong community that is building new open-source resources. To thrive well into the future, it must take further steps to open its technology.</strong></p>
<p>Last week, Dominic, Uwe, and I (Paulus) attended the Z-Wave Alliance member meeting in Austin, Texas. It was the first meeting since we <a href="/blog/2024/02/15/nabu-casa-joins-z-wave-alliance/">became a member</a> and we came with a mission: tell Alliance members about the work done by the open-source community for Z-Wave and find new avenues for collaboration.</p>
<p>Three of us attended, each representing different facets of Z-Wave within the Open Home Foundation: Dominic is the founder and maintainer of Z-Wave JS, which powers the Z-Wave integration in Home Assistant. Uwe leads the development of the Home Assistant Z-Wave stick that we’re working on, and I was there to enable collaborations with other Z-Wave members. Big thanks to <a href="https://www.nabucasa.com/">Home Assistant Cloud subscribers</a> – thanks to you we can do this work full-time at Nabu Casa.</p>
<h3>A little background on Z-Wave</h3>
<p>To use Z-Wave in Home Assistant, our users buy a Z-Wave certified USB stick and combine it with Z-Wave certified devices. Home Assistant then connects to the stick using Z-Wave JS, developed by Dominic, and we’re off to the races. Z-Wave JS was developed completely outside of the Z-Wave Alliance, and is based on the published version of the Z-Wave specification.</p>
<p>Z-Wave wasn’t always this open - Z-Wave used to be owned by a single company, which was later acquired by Silicon Labs. SiLabs decided it was time for change and turned the Z-Wave Alliance into a Standards Development Organization (SDO) that is controlled by its members and a standard that is open.</p>
<p>As it stands, there are still parts of Z-Wave that are not open yet, including the firmware that is running on Z-Wave sticks. I might have mentioned <em>a couple of times,</em> including in my keynote, that we should open up more. It is a good thing to let everyone help fix bugs, improve code quality, and improve diagnostics.</p>
<!--more-->
<h2>Opening Keynote</h2>
<p>One of the conditions that we negotiated when joining the Z-Wave Alliance was that we would be allowed to give an opening keynote to explain the work we have been doing. For the last 8 years, Home Assistant has been doing its own thing with Z-Wave. We have contact with manufacturers of Z-Wave devices via <a href="https://partner.home-assistant.io/">our partner program</a>, but never established an official relationship with the Alliance. We decided that it was time to change that.</p>
<p>We launched the <a href="https://www.openhomefoundation.org/blog/announcing-the-open-home-foundation/">Open Home Foundation</a> last month, a nonprofit that fights for privacy, choice, and sustainability in the smart home – and anyone who lives in one. Open smart home standards like Z-Wave are an important building block for this. With Z-Wave, your data stays at home as communication is fully local. It’s a standard meant to offer consumers choice, and with no reliance on the cloud, devices can continue to work long after a manufacturer ends support, or frankly doesn’t care anymore.</p>
<p>If you follow tech news, you might be wondering now: What about Matter? With the OHF, we believe in choice, including at the standard level. Each standard is built on top of different technologies, and each has pros and cons. Z-Wave is great because it works without Wi-Fi, and its sub-GHz frequency is less busy, allowing it to travel further.</p>
<p class="img"><img src='/images/blog/2024-05-zwave-is-not-dead/paulus-z-wave.jpeg'/>Paulus Schoutsen presenting</p>
<p>In my keynote to the Alliance, I introduced the work we’ve been doing with Home Assistant, Z-Wave JS, and the Open Home Foundation. According to <a href="https://analytics.home-assistant.io">our opt-in analytics</a>, 9.7% of our users use Z-Wave. This also means that 90.3% of installations are one Z-Wave stick away from being able to use Z-Wave. Z-Wave JS has opt-in statistics, which show on average there are 17 Z-Wave devices per network. <strong>Math time:</strong></p>
<p align="center"><b>
1 million active Home Assistant installations<br>
x<br>
9.7% using Z-Wave<br>
x<br>
17 Z-Wave devices<br>
=<br>
1.7 million Z-Wave devices in use </b></p>
<p>When it comes to smart home standards, all big smart home platforms are all-in on Matter and have skipped or forgotten about Z-Wave – except for Home Assistant. We have always featured Z-Wave in our list of integrations and are big promoters of the standard.</p>
<p>This is where I introduced our goal for Z-Wave to the Alliance: we want Z-Wave to be a successful consumer-facing brand. Z-Wave is very popular among companies in the US making security products (like Ring). However, the consumer doesn’t know they are using Z-Wave because it is an implementation detail. This holds Z-Wave back from becoming a rich ecosystem.</p>
<p>For us, success means that there are many manufacturers making Z-Wave devices and that users have an abundance of choice in each product category.</p>
<p class="img"><img src='/images/blog/2024-05-zwave-is-not-dead/keynote.png'/></p>
<p>Z-Wave JS is an independent driver created from the ground up based on the published Z-Wave specification. Dominic has put a lot of effort into this, and his work has formed a community of people passionate about developing the best open Z-Wave driver. Our community has many power users who test Z-Wave JS and make sure it scales and works with both old and new devices.</p>
<p>We are working on getting Z-Wave JS certified to get companies to consider adopting it. Good news on that front – there is already one company that has dropped their 20-year-old Z-Wave stack in favor of Z-Wave JS. Let’s get more on board!</p>
<p>Our efforts to make Z-Wave a success go beyond making an open source Z-Wave driver and smart home platform. We also created the Z-Wave JS Firmware Update service to provide updates for Z-Wave devices. For this service we are currently working with 8 different manufacturers to provide firmware for 187 devices. In my keynote I told the audience that we want to help more manufacturers provide updates to their users.</p>
<p class="img"><img src='/images/blog/2024-05-zwave-is-not-dead/firmware.png'/>The companies that contribute their firmware to the Z-Wave JS Firmware Update service.</p>
<p>In the end, I wrapped up my talk pushing the Alliance to open up more: we all want Z-Wave to succeed. If it is more open, it will be easier for users to adopt. This will lead to more tooling, more apps, more everything. That will, in return, lead to a bigger Z-Wave ecosystem where we can all thrive. Some will do it for sales, or in our case, to drive forward products that value privacy, choice, and sustainability.</p>
<p>We are all in this Alliance to have our devices work together. Let’s not compete on who can best control a Z-Wave light bulb.</p>
<p>OPEN SOURCE!</p>
<h2>Range testing our Z-Wave stick prototype</h2>
<p>One of our team’s first stops at the Z-Wave Summit was attending <a href="https://drzwave.blog/">DrZWave</a>’s range test down at the Colorado River. This was a perfect opportunity to see how well the prototype of our Z-Wave stick performs. While others tested with huge antennas on both sides to reach the longest range possible, we deliberately chose <a href="https://www.silabs.com/development-tools/wireless/efr32xg28-explorer-kit?tab=overview">end devices with tiny antennas</a> to recreate a more real-world scenario. After all, many devices out in the wild don’t have room for big external antennas, and we want to have the best possible experience for our users with existing networks. Also, we tested both classic Z-Wave and Z-Wave Long Range because a majority of existing devices still use classic Z-Wave.</p>
<p>Bikes and scooters weren’t allowed on the bridges and near the water, so Uwe got some exercise that day, walking several miles up and down the river with the end devices in his pockets. Dominic performed the range test using <a href="https://github.com/zwave-js/zwave-js-ui">Z-Wave JS UI</a> and a simple script that sent on/off commands to the end devices to make them blink. Due to encryption, even a single corrupted bit would be noticeable by an interruption of the blinking pattern and missing responses from the end device.</p>
<p>It is barely visible in the photo, but we reached the bridge behind the bridge all the way in the background. We used classic Z-Wave and Z-Wave Long Range, although classic Z-Wave was not as reliable at that distance. That is a 0.7-mile (1.13-km) <strong>line of sight!</strong> With a better antenna on the other side or using EU frequencies (which allow higher transmit power), even further ranges are definitely possible.</p>
<p class="img"><img src='/images/blog/2024-05-zwave-is-not-dead/drzwave.jpeg'/>Left: Dominic, slightly jetlagged, with our stick prototype (green). Right: DrZWave with the controller reference design (purple). Background: Uwe, 0.7 miles away.</p>
<h2>Unplug fest</h2>
<p>Afterward, everyone headed inside for the unplug fest, where manufacturers of end devices and controllers/gateways could connect and test how well they interact with each other. Here’s an example of a HomeSeer prototype that already has great support in Z-Wave JS:</p>
<p class="img"><img src='/images/blog/2024-05-zwave-is-not-dead/unplug.jpeg'/></p>
<p>Since there was still some time left, we took the chance to perform more range tests with our prototype and the reference design, this time indoors going up through multiple layers of concrete. Depending on the end device, we were able to bridge between 2 and 8 floors.</p>
<h2>Z-Wave JS is EVERYWHERE</h2>
<p>Besides powering the Z-Wave integration in Home Assistant, Z-Wave JS is a great tool for development. Built with diagnostics in mind, Z-Wave JS helps understand what the controller and devices are doing and whether they are behaving as expected.</p>
<p>Although we set out to tell people about Z-Wave JS, we learned that a lot of engineers from established companies already use it for development – and in their presentations!</p>
<p class="img"><img src='/images/blog/2024-05-zwave-is-not-dead/slide.png'/></p>
<p>They use it to reproduce issues, do load testing, write scripts to automate certain tasks, and run their own test suites. This includes using the CLI tools to update firmware, for example, to investigate changes between different Z-Wave SDK versions. The Javascript API makes it trivial to perform arbitrary actions and automate things that are hard or impossible to do using UI-based applications.</p>
<p>Another valuable development tool is the Zniffer, a special Z-Wave controller that can capture and decode all Z-Wave radio traffic. Like most of the existing tooling, this requires using Windows. Prior to the summit, Dominic had started working on adding support for Zniffer devices to Z-Wave JS. Although this was still a work in progress, people were already using it for development purposes and told us they were looking forward to it being officially released.</p>
<h2>Conclusion</h2>
<p>Z-Wave is a powerful technology with a large install base, and in certain use cases, it provides real advantages over other connectivity standards. Meeting Alliance members, I can see they are enthusiastic about the future, but it’s the community that will drive the next chapter of Z-Wave. Further opening Z-Wave will empower both the vendors and the community - and help build an open home that serves everyone in it, providing greater privacy, choice, and sustainability.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Nabu Casa joins the Z-Wave Alliance]]></title>
    <link href="https://ivangrod.github.io/blog/2024/02/15/nabu-casa-joins-z-wave-alliance/"/>
    <updated>2024-02-15T00:00:01+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://ivangrod.github.io/blog/2024/02/15/nabu-casa-joins-z-wave-alliance</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>TL;DR: We have joined the Z-Wave Alliance, thanks to revenue from Home Assistant Cloud subscribers, and will start the certification process for Z-Wave JS.</p>
<p><img src='/images/blog/2024-02-zwave/nabucasa-zwa.png' class='no-shadow' /></p>
<p>Z-Wave is a local smart home standard that has been around since 1999. Thanks to operating on sub-Ghz frequencies, it is able to create a reliable mesh network that can span your whole house. Its reliability also made it popular to power brands like Yale locks and Amazon Ring. The Z-Wave standard is developed by a consortium of companies under the <a href="https://z-wavealliance.org/">Z-Wave Alliance</a>.</p>
<p>With Home Assistant, we have integrated Z-Wave since our early days. We first relied on OpenZWave until we transitioned in 2021 to using <a href="https://github.com/zwave-js">Z-Wave JS</a> created by Dominic Griesel. Z-Wave JS is a fully open-source implementation of the Z-Wave protocol. Combined with Home Assistant and a Z-Wave USB stick, it gives our users the best possible Z-Wave experience. Dominic is employed by Nabu Casa and can work full-time on Z-Wave JS thanks to the revenue generated from <a href="https://www.nabucasa.com/">Home Assistant Cloud</a> subscribers (thank you!).</p>
<!--more-->
<p>We have thoroughly tested Z-Wave JS with the Home Assistant community. Our community is from all over the world and has access to a wide variety of Z-Wave devices from all generations. This has ensured that Z-Wave JS is able to deal with devices and their quirks all the way back to the original Z-Wave release.</p>
<p>However, our ambitions for Z-Wave JS are bigger than just making sure we have a rock-solid Z-Wave implementation for you. We want to make it easier for companies to develop Z-Wave controllers and grow the Z-Wave ecosystem. A bigger ecosystem is more appealing for manufacturers to make Z-Wave devices, which results in more choices for our users. And as Z-Wave works locally, it is a local choice.</p>
<p>Today, we are proud to announce that we have joined the Z-Wave Alliance to get Z-Wave JS officially certified. Certification shows other companies that Z-Wave JS is a full and correct implementation of the Z-Wave standard. It will allow other companies to feel confident that they can adopt Z-Wave JS to integrate Z-Wave into their products. HomeSeer, for example, <a href="https://forums.homeseer.com/forum/hs4-products/hs4-plugins/lighting-primary-technology-plug-ins-aa/z-wave-plus-homeseer/1634034-new-z-wave-plus-plugin-under-development#post1634634%0A">has announced</a> that it is migrating its platform to Z-Wave JS. We hope this will open up new opportunities as more companies follow our lead in the future.</p>
<h2>The Open Home</h2>
<p>With Home Assistant, we have a vision for the smart home that we call <a href="/blog/2021/12/23/the-open-home/">the Open Home</a>. It revolves around three core values: privacy, choice, and sustainability. Anything that lives up to those values is worthy of being adopted by our community. It’s why we have previously <a href="/blog/2023/12/04/nabu-casa-at-the-matter-member-meeting/">joined the Connectivity Standards Alliance (CSA)</a> to take part in the development of Matter and Zigbee, and have now joined the Z-Wave Alliance.</p>
<p>Z-Wave aligns with these three values: your data remains local, you can combine Z-Wave devices from any manufacturer, and devices will continue to operate even if the company behind them is no longer around. It is an important standard for the Open Home.</p>
<p>This is why, even though Z-Wave, Zigbee, and Matter are competing standards, we have joined both the Z-Wave Alliance and the CSA and will keep supporting each standard. Not every smart home is the same. Users need to have choice and be able to pick the standard that works best for their home. And competing standards push each other to improve and innovate, ultimately leading to all standards becoming better for users.</p>
<p>As part of the Z-Wave Alliance, we plan on bringing our unique insights as an open source community to the table. We want to make sure that the future direction of the Z-Wave standard continues to remain true to our Open Home values. Just like we do for Zigbee and Matter within the CSA.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
