<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Announcements | Home Assistant]]></title>
  <link href="https://ivangrod.github.io/needlehack-blog/blog/categories/announcements/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://ivangrod.github.io/needlehack-blog/"/>
  <updated>2025-09-23T16:44:51+00:00</updated>
  <id>https://ivangrod.github.io/needlehack-blog/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Home Assistant]]></name>
    
  </author>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Happy 12th Birthday, Home Assistant!]]></title>
    <link href="https://ivangrod.github.io/needlehack-blog/blog/2025/09/17/home-assistant-turns-12/"/>
    <updated>2025-09-17T00:00:01+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://ivangrod.github.io/needlehack-blog/blog/2025/09/17/home-assistant-turns-12</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<img src='/images/blog/2025-09-12th-anniversary/art.webp' style='border: 0;box-shadow: none;' alt="Home Assistant 12th Anniversary">

Every September, we celebrate the anniversary of Home Assistant’s first PR in 2013 – for our 12th birthday, we’re going all in on community again. Last month, we asked for submissions on how Home Assistant helps you, and today we will highlight our favorites! We will also take a look at all the cool milestones over the past year in the project, thanks to contributions from you all, and the new things coming up for the community. <!--more-->

## It’s a communal effort

When I (Missy Quarry) joined as the Community & Social Media Manager in February 2024, I was still new to how an open source project the size of Home Assistant manages its community. Over the past 18 months, I’ve seen Home Assistant community members from all walks of life — whether DIY tinkerers or people simply looking to make small improvements at home — contribute in their own ways. By sharing your stories and inspiring others, you’ve helped the project grow.  For our 12th birthday, I want to celebrate these contributions, no matter the size or complexity. 😌

Before I jump into celebrating all your amazing contributions and how they shape the projects managed by the Open Home Foundation, I have a couple of birthday presents for you. 🎁

First, I’m thrilled to share our [new Community website](/community)! Right now, it’s a simple hub to find community information with ease, but we expect to evolve this over the coming months (or so). You’ll find links to our official community platforms, information on events, and details on meetups, including how to get reimbursed for certain fees as a host. In the future, I’d like to include links to regional communities we’re aware of and showcase more of the kinds of stories I’ll be sharing today.

*Feel like something’s missing from this new page? [Let me know](mailto:community@openhomefoundation.org)!*

Next, we’ve been working hard to do more of our development in the open. Last September, I redesigned the Discord server and in doing so I gated the *Developer* category behind a role. This has made it more difficult to develop in the open with the channels hidden behind a role, so we’re switching things up.

As of this week, the Developer category is now **read-only** for every member. Want to take a peek into the future of Home Assistant? Head to the [#projects channel](https://discord.com/channels/330944238910963714/1346914401508392980) and see what contributors are talking about! Want to join in and contribute with either your feedback or skills? I’ve created [an info thread](https://discord.com/channels/330944238910963714/1346952081881436331) for the channel that explains how to assign yourself either the Developer or Designer role and unlock the ability to chat in the threads.

Let’s jump into those submitted stories now… 🤩

## Happily ever after

In my opinion, the best thing about Home Assistant is its flexibility - you can integrate such a wide range of devices into it and use their data to build a unique-to-your-home experience. And that’s exactly why I wanted to hear how you, the community, use it in your own home to benefit you. Here are my favorite stories you submitted - I hope one inspires your next project. ✨

- [A coffee automation to improve Home Approval Factor](https://jordan.roher.me/projects/home-automation/). ☕️ Jordan made a morning automation to avoid having the coffee grinder grind his morning mood.

- u/katschung helped their girlfriend fully accept Home Assistant by [creating a dashboard with a retrogame-style floor plan](https://www.reddit.com/r/homeassistant/comments/1hrkku1/pokemon_style_floorplan/). 🕹️

- Sythsaz uses Home Assistant to make sure their pupper is fed. 🐾 “*I've managed to make it so my dog's food auto emails the vet then the response to the email gets put on my calendar so I know how long a bag of food lasts as well as adding the receipts to Google Drive.*”

- Inspired by [PowerDisplayESPHome](https://github.com/johannyren/PowerDisplayESPHome/tree/main), JannickBlmndl [made an LED matrix](https://gitlab.com/JannickBlmndl/ESPHome-Dynamic-Prices-LEDMatrix) that helps their household be more sustainable by being energy flexible. It displays the live energy prices from their energy provider. 📊

- [Tano Spirits](https://www.youtube.com/@TanoSpirits) in Melbourne, Australia, uses Home Assistant to automate their Japanese Shochu distillery, inspired by the brewing automations at [Little Island Brewing Co](https://libc.co/brewing-process/) in Singapore. 🍻

- Several years ago, HillPhantom found that Home Assistant wasn’t quite ready for him. Over the past year, though, he’s now got Ollama set up with his Home Assistant Voice Preview Edition and has been building guides on how to make your own [mmWave radar sensors in Home Assistant](https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Gb-4l93st8A). 👋🏻

- Over just a few weeks, Pieter van Kampen recently integrated 190 devices that respond to voice control and more than 1200 active entities from his KNX home to create over 30 automations to help with everything from mowing the lawn to controlling shades based on the sun’s location and intensity. 🪟

- MB used Zigbee buttons to help collect data for their son’s doctor after he developed some trouble sleeping. This gave excellent insight for the doctor to start looking into causes, and they even used the system remotely while doing further evaluation. 📈

- Graham Hosking took automations to another level (before we did) with his [AI Automation Suggester](https://github.com/ITSpecialist111/ai_automation_suggester) and [Automation Inspector](https://github.com/ITSpecialist111/Automation-Inspector). It takes the load off your brain by helping come up with new, clever automations! 🤖

- Wessam Lauf fell down the rabbit hole that is Home Assistant once he got his setup running. Inspired by the Graphite theme and after some LLM vibe-coding, he wrote a template for his very own theme, [Frosted Glass](https://github.com/wessamlauf/homeassistant-frosted-glass-themes) - now available in [HACS](https://www.hacs.xyz/). 🎨

- Too many of us anthropomorphize our homes, telling it to chill out when five things break the same day. Biofects took that to heart and created this [Home Assistant avatar](https://streamable.com/hnoc63) for his home (here’s a bonus, nightmare fuel [first version](https://streamable.com/xah2va)). 🫣

## Developers! 👏🏻 Developers! 👏🏻 Developers! 👏🏻

Our community is more than developers, it’s true. But we wouldn’t be the [largest open source project](https://github.blog/news-insights/octoverse/octoverse-2024/) on GitHub if we didn’t have a vibrant and active developer community. This ship sails largely due to their contributions, and we genuinely appreciate all of their efforts.

That’s why we’re eager to interview community members when we open new roles at the foundation. We’ve employed community members like [Joostlek](https://github.com/joostlek) (who designed the new [Integration Quality Scale](https://developers.home-assistant.io/docs/core/integration-quality-scale/) and helps onboard new integrations into Core), [Timo](https://github.com/TimoPtr) (who is our first ever Android developer and has focused on [polishing the Android app](/blog/2025/07/23/companion-app-for-android/)), and [Maxim](https://github.com/maximmaxim345) (a talented developer from the Music Assistant community who works on both Music Assistant and ESPHome and is one of our newest additions to the team). Their contributions have helped shape how things work around here, but it was their contributions as community members that helped pave the way for their joining the foundation. These are just a select few of the *several* new hires at the foundation who were active community members.

(Have you checked our [jobs page](https://jobs.ashbyhq.com/openhomefoundation/) recently to see what roles are open? 👀)

With our community of contributors and working with Nabu Casa on the hardware design, we have successfully launched a few new pieces of hardware. The [Home Assistant Voice Preview Edition](/voice-pe/) brought in language experts from every corner of the world to help ensure our language coverage is the most robust in the industry. Thanks to contributors, we support languages like Greek, Icelandic, and more recently Irish Gaeilge! 😎 We had community contributors help make sure the Home Assistant [Connect ZWA-2](/connect/zwa-2/) was prepared for launch last month. Sincerely, we couldn’t be more grateful for your support and efforts in these spaces.

Here are some fun stats from our GitHub contributors ([commits on our Core repo](https://github.com/home-assistant/core/graphs/contributors?from=9%2F9%2F2023)):

- Last 12 months (Sept - Aug) - 14,385
- Previous 12 months - 14,503

A SPECIAL CONGRATULATIONS to [bdraco](https://github.com/bdraco), who just last week surpassed [balloob](https://github.com/balloob) (the founder of Home Assistant) as the contributor with the most commits!

<div class="contain nb">
    <img src="/images/blog/2025-09-12th-anniversary/contributors.webp" alt="Top 8 contributors of all time for home-assistant/core" style="width:100%;max-width:700px;">
    The top 8 contributors of all time in home-assistant/core👏🏻
</div>

This is just a small peek into all the hard work that goes into maintaining Home Assistant - we have more repositories than just Core, and every single contribution is valued.

Honorable dev mention from the submitted community stories - I couldn’t leave Joostlek’s (joke) submission out. 🤣

- Our very own Head of Developer Relations (his words), Joost Lekkerkerker, says Home Assistant helps keep him off the street. He’s just launched [his new blog](https://joostlek.dev/what-is-a-smart-home/) that talks about his vision of a smart home, and how he was inspired to not buy Tuya Wi-Fi lights after seeing my experience with some path lights.

## Our humble gratitude

Community is the core of what we do and the heart of Home Assistant. We thrive because you care and contribute your valuable time to support our collective success. Whether you found our platform because you wanted more privacy from big tech, were intrigued by the number of choices implemented into a single app, or needed something to track your sustainability efforts — you support our values every day. Thanks for choosing us, and thank you for all you do to help support the foundation and the projects we maintain.

A very special thanks to all our [Home Assistant Cloud](/cloud/) subscribers and anyone who has purchased our official Home Assistant hardware. These support the full-time development of Home Assistant (along with ESPHome, Music Assistant, and so much more), and are the easiest way to ensure these projects keep getting cool new features!

We have more things coming down the line for you. In the near future, we plan on announcing a new merch store 👕. In the first half of next year, I’ll announce when Home Assistant Community Day 2026 will be. We’re already working with Nabu Casa on the next exciting hardware announcement (no spoilers…for now). And that’s not even touching the industry events we plan on attending, the State of the Open Home, and so much more. I’m excited to take you all on the journey we’re already working on over the next 12 months, and I’m always looking forward to another year of amazing contributions. 😌

<script>
    if (!document.cookie.split('; ').find(row => row.startsWith('12th-blog-confetti='))) {
        const d = new Date();
        d.setTime(d.getTime() + (24*60*60*1000)); // Once a day only
        let expires = "expires="+ d.toUTCString();
        document.cookie = "12th-blog-confetti=1;" + expires + ";path=/";

        const script = document.createElement('script');
        script.src = 'https://cdn.jsdelivr.net/npm/canvas-confetti@1.9.3/dist/confetti.browser.min.js';
        script.onload = () => {
            // launch confetti. Full screen, bottom anchor
            confetti({ particleCount: 500, gravity: 1, spread: 120, scalar: 1.5, startVelocity: 150, ticks: 200, angle: 90, origin: { y: 1.4, x: 0.5 }});
        };
        document.head.appendChild(script);
    }
</script>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Z-Wave reborn - Home Assistant Connect ZWA-2]]></title>
    <link href="https://ivangrod.github.io/needlehack-blog/blog/2025/08/13/home-assistant-connect-zwa-2/"/>
    <updated>2025-08-13T00:00:01+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://ivangrod.github.io/needlehack-blog/blog/2025/08/13/home-assistant-connect-zwa-2</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<img src='/images/blog/2025-08-home-assistant-connect-zwa-2/art.webp' style='border: 0;box-shadow: none;' alt="Z-Wave reborn - Home Assistant Connect ZWA-2">

Introducing the [Home Assistant Connect ZWA-2](/connect/zwa-2/), the ultimate way to connect Z-Wave devices to Home Assistant. Between its optimized antenna and seamless integration with Home Assistant, it should be a big upgrade for anyone using Z-Wave today.

If you’re not using Z-Wave, it's time to take a second look, as Connect ZWA-2 is a different beast. It might be just what you need to reach that tricky spot in your home… or even beyond. Connect ZWA-2 supports Z-Wave Long Range, and this modern take on the standard delivers exceptional reach along with more responsive, battery-efficient devices. Every home is different, but our testers have managed connections in places they once thought impossible.

Join the smart home range revolution for **$69 or €59** (that’s the recommended MSRP, and pricing will vary by retailer). For quick details, specs, and where to buy, visit our [Home Assistant Connect ZWA-2 page](/connect/zwa-2/). It's available for purchase today. Read on to learn what goes into the ultimate Z-Wave upgrade.

<a href="/connect/zwa-2" style="display:block;text-align:center;"><img src='/images/blog/2025-08-home-assistant-connect-zwa-2/buy.webp' style='border: 0;box-shadow: none;' alt="Buy the Home Assistant Connect ZWA-2"></a>
<!--more-->

## We love open standards

Open standards let you connect devices directly to Home Assistant for local, private control, and keep working for years, even if the manufacturer disappears. To make connecting these standards as seamless as possible, we like to build our own hardware.

In late 2022, we launched [Home Assistant Connect ZBT-1](/connectzbt1/) (formerly SkyConnect), a USB adapter for Zigbee and Thread. It made both protocols much easier to get started with, and sales helped fund Home Assistant development. We knew the next standard to tackle was Z-Wave, and after another couple of hardware launches ([Home Assistant Green](/green) and [Voice Preview Edition](/voice-pe/)), we finally had the time to do it right.

### Why Z-Wave?

If you’re new to Z-Wave, its key advantage over other open standards is its use of sub-GHz radio waves, which are better at getting through thick walls and reaching across large households. While Wi-Fi, Bluetooth, Zigbee, and Thread all compete for the same crowded airspace (2.4 GHz), Z-Wave operates in its own much quieter spectrum (865-926 MHz). Z-Wave is great for range, but its new [Z-Wave Long Range variant](https://z-wavealliance.org/what-is-z-wave-long-range-how-does-it-differ-from-z-wave/) builds even further on this… _but more on that later_.

As the standard is over two decades old, it's had a lot of time to iron out any kinks, but it also has over 4,500 certified devices to choose from. Our opt-in stats show over 130,000 Home Assistant households are using Z-Wave today. Several [Works with Home Assistant](https://works-with.home-assistant.io/) partners are building amazing Z-Wave products, including [Zooz](/integrations/zooz/), [Shelly](/integrations/shelly_zwave/), [Ultraloq](/integrations/ultraloq/), [Leviton](/integrations/leviton_z_wave/), and [Homeseer](/integrations/homeseer/). You can also go to any local marketplace and pick up any working Z-Wave smart device, no matter how old, and it will still connect with Home Assistant!

## Connect ZWA-2 in-depth

We’ve learned a lot about hardware since the launch of Connect ZBT-1, and we also knew we could breathe some new life into Z-Wave on Home Assistant. Making this device was the start of us leveling up the Connect platform and establishing our **second generation**, which is all about building the most performant and open design. That is why we jumped straight to _two_ for this Connect ZWA-2!

### Go big or go home

To be the most performant, we knew we had to ditch the “stick” form factor. It was never ideal, as USB ports can output a lot of interference. We even shipped a USB extender with Connect ZBT-1, and urged people to use it, as it kept the device away from any noisy components. Instead of building a stick we built an _adapter_, which includes an optimized standalone antenna and base that connects to your Home Assistant system with a USB cable.

<img src='/images/blog/2025-08-home-assistant-connect-zwa-2/precisely-engineered.webp' style='border: 0;box-shadow: none;' alt="Comparison of the Home Assistant Connect ZWA-2 antenna to other Z-Wave antennas, showing the size difference">

We’re not compensating for anything; a big antenna does make a big difference. For starters, you need an antenna that's the right size for your wavelength. As Z-Wave is in the sub-GHz, this means the antenna has to be longer than your average Wi-Fi antenna (about 33 cm or a foot is the sweet spot).

You need to optimize not just the antenna, but also the base of the device (also known as the _ground plane_). Our hardware experts really went deep into all the physics involved, and the results speak for themselves. Basically, by choosing the right ratio of antenna to base, the two work in harmony to maximize the range and reliability of the signal.

While some Z-Wave adapters may claim they can hit the maximum transmit levels with their postage-stamp-sized antennas, that can sometimes come with a lot of interference. We’ve engineered away that problem. Connect ZWA-2 can speak loudly and clearly 🗣️, and what’s even more important, it's a great listener 👂.

### Positioning is everything

Having a big optimized antenna is great, but placement is almost as important. Its sturdy base and good-sized USB cable allow it to be placed in the right spot. No more will you have a dangling dongle hidden behind a server cabinet. We even put in an accelerometer to ensure people position the antenna upright, this ensures devices are in the sweet spot of the antenna. If you place it on its side, it will subtly blink the status light at the top.

### All the Z-Wave

Inside Connect ZWA-2, we include the latest Z-Wave 800 chip, which supports all Z-Wave devices. We’re also Z-Wave certified, giving you that extra peace of mind. This, combined with Home Assistant’s industry-leading Z-Wave software, means Z-Wave has never been this good. On your certified smart devices, you might see Security 2 (S2), SmartStart, Z-Wave Plus, or Z-Wave Plus V2 — don’t worry, we support it all. One new feature we support that is getting people very excited is Z-Wave Long Range👇.

### Go long

<img src='/images/blog/2025-08-home-assistant-connect-zwa-2/supports-all-devices.webp' style='border: 0;box-shadow: none;' alt="Isometric view of the Home Assistant Connect ZWA-2 revealing the internal PCB featuring the Z-Wave 800 chipset">

Combining Z-Wave's natural abilities with an optimized antenna has given us some impressive range, but we took it a few steps further. We added Z-Wave Long Range to Connect ZWA-2, which might be one of the most substantial updates to Z-Wave yet.

<div class="alert">
    <p><strong>Z-Wave Long Range</strong><br> Long Range doesn’t use mesh, where devices relay messages through each other to reach the hub. Instead, each device talks straight to your hub, which brings some benefits. It runs on the same frequency as regular Z-Wave but at a higher power, and uses new technology that lets it reach farther, handle more devices, respond faster, and save battery. Right now, it is only available in North America and Europe, and the selection of compatible devices is still growing. This is just scratching the surface; for more on this impressive tech, read a <a href="https://z-wavealliance.org/what-is-z-wave-long-range-how-does-it-differ-from-z-wave/" target="_blank">full breakdown</a> from our friends at the Z-Wave Alliance.</p>
</div>

Z-Wave Long Range is different enough that it needs its own separate network. Connect ZWA-2 can run both Z-Wave and Z-Wave Long Range **at the same time**. When you add a Long Range capable device to Home Assistant, the setup wizard lets you choose which network to use. This way, you get the best of both worlds: a strong mesh network for your older devices, and the reach of Long Range for the newest devices that include support.

### How long?

<p class="img">
<img src='/images/blog/2025-08-home-assistant-connect-zwa-2/zwa-2-prototype-testing.webp' style='border: 0;box-shadow: none;' alt="Dominic with our stick prototype alongside DrZWave with the controller reference design. Uwe is on the other bridge, 0.7 miles away">
See that bridge in the background? Our prototype connected to a device all the way over there.
</p>

People are getting some impressive results with ZWA-2:

- You might have seen our range testing [in a previous blog](/blog/2024/05/08/zwave-is-not-dead/#range-testing-our-z-wave-stick-prototype). Since then, we’ve optimized the design and achieved a line-of-sight range of 1.5 kilometers (0.9 miles) 🤯. This was under less than ideal circumstances (raining and within a car), and we think we could go even further.

- The certifying engineer said it was “the best range she had ever seen”.

- Another test had it communicating via Z-Wave Long Range through several floors of concrete.

- Testers with outdoor lights and internal brick walls have commented on how this is the first time they’ve had reliable connections with devices.

- Interesting Long Range use cases have included smart mailboxes that notify you when _you’ve got mail_, or contact sensors on garden gates.

Every home and setup is different, so we can’t definitively say how far your devices will span. What we can say is that nothing else we’ve tested comes close to what Connect ZWA-2 can do.

### Built for Home Assistant

<img src='/images/blog/2025-08-home-assistant-connect-zwa-2/plug-and-play.webp' style='border: 0;box-shadow: none;' alt="Home Assistant Connect ZWA-2 connected to a Home Assistant Green">

Whenever we build new hardware, we step up our software development to match. You may have noticed a lot of love going into Z-Wave for Home Assistant. All Z-Wave users benefit from this, and when people buy Connect ZWA-2, they’re helping fund this development.

Connect ZWA-2 is built for Home Assistant, and because of this, it’s super easy to get started with. We’ve built Connect ZWA-2 to support every region, no matter where you buy it from. When you plug in Connect ZWA-2, it automatically detects and sets your region using the location configured in your Home Assistant system.

We’ve built handy wizards to help you set up your first Z-Wave network and to guide you in setting up new devices. A wizard also helps you quickly migrate from most Z-Wave adapters to Connect ZWA-2 in a couple of clicks. We also have the ability to update the firmware of Connect ZWA-2 right from Home Assistant, and update the firmware over-the-air (OTA) of Z-Wave devices in a single click.

### ESP inside

<p class="img">
<img src='/images/blog/2025-08-home-assistant-connect-zwa-2/zwa-2-pcb.webp' style='border: 0;box-shadow: none;' alt="Front and back of the PCB outside the shell of the Home Assistant Connect ZWA-2">
I’ll save you the time opening it up; here is the front and back of the PCB.
</p>

As always, we’ve made Connect ZWA-2 easy to open. Just pop out the rubber feet and remove the four Phillips screws, with no glue or clips to get in the way. If you do open it up, you’ll see a familiar sight, an ESP32-S3. We’re using it as a USB controller, and it's not running ESPHome. Yes, it does have a “Wi-Fi antenna”, but we’re not using it. We’ve provided a lot of easily accessible pins/pads, open source firmware files, unlocked bootloader, and good documentation, so feel free to tinker. We’ll also provide all the files to allow you to 3D-print the outer casing.

### Blending into the home

<img src='/images/blog/2025-08-home-assistant-connect-zwa-2/in-the-home.webp' alt="Home Assistant Connect ZWA-2 sitting on a shelf next to a plant and some books">

It's no small feat to make something 33 cm (1 ft) long look so subtle in the home. We’ve modeled its design after a candle and even used the top of the antenna as a status indicator. Its quality injection-molded exterior has a premium feel and shares many design cues from our sleek-looking Voice Preview Edition.

## Join the smart home range revolution

Last year, we proclaimed in a blog that “[Z-Wave is not dead](/blog/2024/05/08/zwave-is-not-dead/)”, and this hardware is a testament to that belief. Even with new technologies being released every week, there’s still room to innovate with something tried and tested. We will always support technology that respects your privacy, allows you to control your devices without the cloud, all while keeping the things you already have in your home running for years to come.

After 1600 words on a Z-Wave adapter, we’re obviously very proud of what we’ve built and excited to see what amazing things people will do with this labor of love. So, whether you’re a Z-Wave veteran or just interested in cool new technology, take a look at [Home Assistant Connect ZWA-2](/connect/zwa-2/) today.
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Community Day 2025 Wrap-up]]></title>
    <link href="https://ivangrod.github.io/needlehack-blog/blog/2025/06/24/community-day-2025-wrap-up/"/>
    <updated>2025-06-24T00:00:01+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://ivangrod.github.io/needlehack-blog/blog/2025/06/24/community-day-2025-wrap-up</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<img src='/images/blog/2025-06-community-day-wrap-up/art.jpg' style='border: 0;box-shadow: none;' alt="Pictures of multiple community day meetups">

Our first Home Assistant Community Day was a humbling success --- we knew that the community had a desire to have something coordinated like this, but we really did not expect just how widely this would spread. 💖

So much happened in such a short window of time, so let's talk about how this year's event went and what the future looks like for Home Assistant meetups.<!--more-->

## It started with a question...

Home Assistant Community Day was born from a conversation last year where we asked, "Would the community even *want* this?" We dropped hints here and there to test how y'all would react to a worldwide event, and after weeks of planning, the response to the event announcement was overwhelmingly positive. 🤩

First, **THANK YOU** 🙏🏻 to all **the hosts** for their local coordination, **community members** who showed up, and **the venues** that made all this possible. I learned so much with your help, and it will make next year's Community Day one to remember.

## ...that turned into a movement...

When I announced Home Assistant Community Day, I didn't give hosts a lot to work with. I didn't want the community to think they had to fit into a specific format, and wanted it to be unique to their region. It became clear pretty quickly what information was missing and what people wanted guidance on. For example, some asked for suggestions on what types of venues to book or which activities could make the event more interactive, such as quizzes or presentations. Your questions helped us make it easier for hosts to build cool events, thank you for those!  

All around the world, everyone came together to talk about Home Assistant (and its related projects). You swapped hardware, you showed off your automations or dashboards, you participated in quizzes, and you formed new bonds with people in your area who share your passion for Home Assistant. Some people had custom swag printed, others received hardware from a couple of our [Works With Home Assistant](https://works-with.home-assistant.io/) partners, and one group had a Hackathon event the day before! So many great photos were shared from the events that we can't possibly include them all here! You can find plenty more by searching #HADay2025 on social media or by checking the [Discord meetup thread](https://discord.com/channels/330944238910963714/1364989531069091920/1375786903324070042) for this event. It was seriously one of the most uplifting things I've had the pleasure to not only facilitate, but also witness. 🥰

## ...but not without complications

Swag was an unexpected complication. When I first announced the day, we planned to have me order the merch and then send it off to the hosts. This would require collecting addresses and sending packages to people around the world, and we realized quickly that the logistics of that would end up a mess.  Instead, we made the sticker designs (along with the Luma calendar invite graphic) publicly available for the hosts to print something locally.

When we did this, we (as the Open Home Foundation) committed to reimbursing the hosts for these swag purchases, along with venue fees or other reasonable expenses they might have on the day. The idea being that no host should be out of pocket for supporting their local Home Assistant community. You support us (by contributing time or by being [Home Assistant Cloud](/cloud/) subscribers), and we want to give back to the community in any way we can.

I'm excited to share that we plan on using those same guidelines for any community meetup, not just the ones that happen on Community Day! 👏🏻 We're building a new community page where all of these details will be available, so stay tuned for more information.

## Some stats for the nerds

We had [82 events](https://lu.ma/haday2025) with over 1,600 registered guests, spanning nearly every corner of the globe. The events started in New Zealand and ended on the West Coast of North America. This meant we had meetups held from 10 pm May 23 to midnight May 25 (UTC time), that's over 26 hours of constant partying! 🥳

We had events in every major region except Australia! Most meetups were in Europe and North America --- probably not too surprising for most. The smallest events had 2 registered guests, and the event that had the largest number of registered guests was Utrecht, with 200!

With an average of 20 people attending a meetup, we know that we can advise a lower capacity limit for future events. This will be included as part of the guidelines we'll have on that new community page I mentioned above.

## Keep the fun going!

Many hosts told me that they've created a new space for the attendees to chat or that they were going to start doing some regular meetups (some have done both!). Since Luma worked so well for us for Community Day, I've created [a general calendar for meetups](https://lu.ma/homeassistant)! I also have [graphic assets](https://drive.google.com/drive/folders/1i7Ta0910ozc66jKqhib5fCrOpYyt9b_J?usp=share_link) publicly available for your Luma event and any social media you'd like to post your event on --- use the 1:1 ratio image for the invite image on Luma. There are two events live there now, way to go Chile (Santiago) and Belgium (Hasselt)! 🤩

While we don't have a solid date for next year's Home Assistant Community Day, I can at least let you know that it will not be in May and instead later in the year. I'm aiming to give you at least a two-month heads-up for when it will be this time. We're planning on doing something bigger and I can't wait to do it all again with y'all next year. 😌

P.S. - Did you spot our [refreshed Creator Network](https://creators.home-assistant.io) page yet? 👀
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Roadmap 2025: A Truly Smart Home through Collective Intelligence]]></title>
    <link href="https://ivangrod.github.io/needlehack-blog/blog/2025/05/09/roadmap-2025h1/"/>
    <updated>2025-05-09T00:00:01+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://ivangrod.github.io/needlehack-blog/blog/2025/05/09/roadmap-2025h1</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<img alt="Devices, Automations, Dashboards, Voice & Music, Frontend" src="/images/blog/2025-05-roadmap-2025h1/roadmap-2025-cover.png" class='no-shadow'/>

It's been a year since we launched [our first roadmap](/blog/2024/06/12/roadmap-2024h1/) for Home Assistant, which means it's time to launch this year's first update! In 2025, we're building on our direction to make Home Assistant easier to use for everyone in your household, and taking it to the next level by making smart homes more intuitive, proactive, and user-friendly. 🚀

This centers on helping Home Assistant understand devices in their context, and cataloging every device that works with Home Assistant through a new project, Device Database. And we will do this the Home Assistant way --- through the power of our community and our collective intelligence. (...but that's not all! The roadmap also covers many product areas we are aiming to work on from automation to voice to dashboard [and more](#and-thats-not-all-for-this-year)!)

If you're new to our roadmaps or curious about how they guide the development of Home Assistant, be sure to check out [our introduction](/blog/2024/06/12/roadmap-introduction/) to Home Assistant roadmaps. As always, your feedback is incredibly valuable, so please give us your thoughts in the comments.
<!-- TOC -->

- [One year on the road](#one-year-on-the-road)
- [The smart home administrator as an inventor](#the-smart-home-administrator-as-an-inventor)
- [From shared wisdom to collective intelligence](#from-shared-wisdom-to-collective-intelligence)
- [Putting Devices in Context](#putting-devices-in-context)
- [Introducing the Device Database](#introducing-the-device-database)
- [And that's not all for this year!](#and-thats-not-all-for-this-year)
- [Laying the Groundwork for a Truly Smart Home](#laying-the-groundwork-for-a-truly-smart-home)

<!-- /TOC -->
<!--more-->
## One year on the road

Last year, we introduced [our very first roadmap](/blog/2024/06/12/roadmap-2024h1/)---and it wasn't just plans on paper. It marked a new chapter for Home Assistant: one where we made our direction clear, set ambitious goals, and invited the whole community along for the ride.

In [2024](/blog/2024/06/12/roadmap-2024h1/), we focused on building a smart home that has a high Home Approval Factor: helping both the maintainer and residents of the smart home unlock more value from Home Assistant without needing to be an expert. This was done by improving the touchpoints that all members of the household will interact with, such as automations, dashboards, and voice interactions, while maintaining the power and depth of the platform for our power users and admins.

The real challenge lay in building a roadmap from scratch. That meant not only poring through and prioritizing every single feature request, but also increasing transparency and building trust in the roadmap within our organization and our community as a beacon that can help guide the development of the project. Thanks to the feedback, energy, and contributions from our global community, we've made huge strides. In the past year, we tackled some of the biggest pain points, such as drag-and-drop dashboard improvements, automation grouping, standard voice assistant hardware, better automated backups, and more.

Now, in 2025, we are ready to lay the groundwork for the next big step forward: Making Home Assistant *truly smart* through our collective effort and intelligence.

## The smart home administrator as an inventor

Home Approval Factor means that a successful smart home isn't just great for the person who set it up, but for everyone who lives there. Whether it's your partner, kids, or roommates, we want Home Assistant to feel intuitive and supportive for the whole household.

In some ways, being a smart home administrator is like being an inventor (or, as we would say, a product manager). To be a great inventor, you need to understand your users. What are their needs? What solutions can you invent to solve their problems? How do you know you solved their problems? Can you improve upon the solution?

Home Assistant provides all the building blocks for our administrators to build whatever they want and let their imaginations run wild, and better yet, it's easier than ever with the improvements we made last year! However, that's also the curse of a blank slate. Inventing fun and hyper-personalized solutions for niche problems is a major appeal of Home Assistant, but sometimes, maintenance of a smart home can be a chore --- not every single problem requires reinventing the wheel.

The reality today is that, according to our [community survey](/blog/2025/04/16/state-of-the-open-home-recap/#research), just 46% of partners and only 27% of children of long-time Home Assistant users are directly interacting with Home Assistant. That's a big gap, and it highlights a broader challenge: Even the most experienced smart home administrators don't always have the complete picture of their household's needs. They may not realize what would help until something goes wrong. And it's unreasonable to expect everyone to be an expert in everything --- from automations to dashboards to onboarding new users.

## From shared wisdom to collective intelligence

<p class='img'><img alt="wisdom spread across social, chats, and videos" src="/images/blog/2025-05-roadmap-2025h1/shared-wisdom.jpg"/></p>

Right now, if a smart home admin wants to improve their setup, they have to go hunting---through our community forums, GitHub repos, Reddit threads, YouTube videos, Discord chats... you name it---trying to find tips and tricks that apply to their specific case. You share incredible wisdom with each other every day, but much of it is scattered, short-lived, or hard to apply without lots of customization.

We believe it's time for a smarter system.

What if Home Assistant could learn from our community's best ideas and use that knowledge to proactively suggest improvements? What if it could guide users based on what others have done in similar situations? That's the vision we're working toward: using collective intelligence to power a truly smart home.

<p class='img'><img alt="organized shared wisdom is collective intelligence" src="/images/blog/2025-05-roadmap-2025h1/collective-intelligence.jpg"/></p>

To get there, Home Assistant needs to *understand* what's in the home. Inside each home, there are the people, the spaces, and the devices. This year, we will start with helping Home Assistant understand devices in terms of (1) **context**: what each device is and how it is used, and (2) **information**: every device that works with Home Assistant and how it is supported.

## Putting Devices in Context

Today, most devices in Home Assistant show up as a bundle of entities: a temperature sensor here, a switch there. This is by design --- we want to provide the ultimate flexibility in configuring your system, and will continue to do so. However, it is not without disadvantages.

<p class='img'><img alt="Fridge as a series of entities" src="/images/blog/2025-05-roadmap-2025h1/devices-without-context.jpg"/></p>

For example, we don't always know that those entities together form, say, a fridge, which is essentially a mini house of its own: It may have temperature sensors, a door sensor, a light, and so on, but Home Assistant cannot assume them as any other sensors or lights within a room. Without that context, Home Assistant can't do much beyond letting users build their own dashboards and automations from scratch.

As you add more devices, entities pile up, and Home Assistant starts to lose the thread of what's actually in the home. Your smart home should become more powerful as you add more devices, but at the cost of the difficulty of maintaining them also increasing exponentially.

When we **put devices in context**, everything changes. A fridge becomes more than a list of entities --- it becomes an actual device that can have a dedicated dashboard, default automations, and contextual voice commands.

<p class='img'><img alt="Dashboards, Automation and Voice in context" src="/images/blog/2025-05-roadmap-2025h1/device-context.jpg"/></p>

Here's how context unlocks a more streamlined experience across the platform:

- **Voice:** Assist can currently source the right sensor if it knows the area of the device. In the future, we can also intelligently exclude irrelevant sensors from a voice query. For example, "What's the temperature in the kitchen?" shouldn't return the freezer's internal temperature.
- **Dashboards:** Integrations can provide customized cards and dashboards right from the start, providing a much more streamlined experience. For example, we can provide a fridge dashboard. It works with other devices, too. Imagine a car dashboard or a 3D printer dashboard.
- **Automations:** By understanding what devices a user has and how they are commonly used, we can intelligently suggest automations created by our community. For example, "fridge door left open" or "fridge water leakage" alerts can be provided without building them manually from scratch.

This will be a core architectural change that will be proposed and discussed in the coming months. We're building on what our contributors already share in integrations: knowledge about how devices are structured and how they should behave. My hope is that this will provide the framework for our contributors to contribute dashboards and automation blueprints to our code in exciting new ways.

## Introducing the Device Database

To make all this work, we also need a centralized, structured place to store and share device knowledge. That's where the Device Database---a brand new project from the Open Home Foundation---comes in.

Think of it as a source of truth created, curated, and validated by the community. A place where we gather everything from metadata (like power usage or infrared codes) to factual information (setup instructions such as how to add or reset a device) to real-world setup insights and community creations (such as automation examples). It will contain information users intentionally submit to the database, nothing will be collected automatically without your explicit consent.

It's more than just having all device documentation in one place. We want to universalize all our collective experiences about devices in one place, which is more accessible, centralized, and structured than online websites and chat rooms.

With the Device Database, users both old and new can easily make well-informed choices and pick the best Home Assistant-compatible devices for them based on real usage experiences, allowing them to easily make decisions based on open home values --- privacy, choice, and sustainability.

The data will be used and cross-referenced in Home Assistant and other Open Home Foundation projects, and acts as the backbone of their integrations. For example, a future infrared integration can hypothetically benefit from having access to readily available infrared codes from the database.

<p class='img'><img alt="Protocols, device database, feeding choice" src="/images/blog/2025-05-roadmap-2025h1/working-together.png"/></p>

This isn't something we can build alone. We're relying on the strength of our global community to turn this vision into reality, and we're backing it up with our infrastructure, engineering efforts, and partnerships:

- The [Open Home Foundation](https://www.openhomefoundation.org/) is here to provide the framework to help us collect and collaborate on knowledge easily and safely.
- We're working with [Nabu Casa](https://www.nabucasa.com/)---our commercial partner---to create the most reliable hardware antennas that support more open protocols, such as Z-Wave, Zigbee, Bluetooth, and more, to expand the Home Assistant ecosystem.
- The [Works with Home Assistant program](https://works-with.home-assistant.io/) is being strengthened to make it easier to find trusted, high-quality devices for the platform, as you may have witnessed with the [numerous new partners](/blog/categories/works-with-home-assistant/) joining in the past few months.

The result? A system where no admin has to figure everything out in isolation on their own. Home Assistant can suggest, guide, adapt, and point users in the right direction, by drawing from the collective intelligence of the community (instead of scraping user data involuntarily like what Big Tech does).

## And that's not all for this year!

<p class='img'><img alt="Devices, Automations, Dashboards, Voice & Music, Frontend" src="/images/blog/2025-05-roadmap-2025h1/roadmap-2025.png"/></p>

While device context and the Device Database are the major themes of this year's roadmap, it doesn't mean that we are dropping everything else that does not fit. We're continuing work on other parts of the product experience:

- A complete revamp of our automation triggers and conditions to make them both easier to use and more powerful.
- A navigation and design system overhaul to improve feature discovery.
- Continued improvements to make dashboards easier to use out of the box, including a new default dashboard and more.
- Enhanced privacy controls for users, guests, and public access (Yes, I am aware of that.)
- Easier setup for Music Assistant.
- Make Assist more conversational, such as the ability to confirm and clarify a query.
- Continued explorations in using LLMs to improve the overall user experience beyond voice.

In the meantime, we are working on making our roadmap more publicly accessible, so that you can discuss and track our progress with us! Stay tuned.

## Laying the Groundwork for a Truly Smart Home

This roadmap isn't about the flashy latest tech fad (what is it now anyway?) or abstract features. It's about creating the enduring foundation to allow our community to build something greater than all of us together: a smart home platform that learns, grows, and adapts --- with full respect for privacy, choice, and sustainability.

The central theme of the roadmap is that making Home Assistant smarter starts with understanding context, such as knowing what devices are and how they're used, and we will use this collective intelligence to supercharge the main pillars of the user experience --- automations, voice, and dashboards.

We're making maintenance of a smart home easier, by making it less like a mandatory chore while still keeping the fun of tinkering (say, you wanna go wild on YAML), and by creating tools to help admins solve problems they don't even know they have yet. We believe that, as our advanced users continue to tinker with their systems, their creations and discoveries will also benefit and elevate every user's smart home.

We can't wait to work on these initiatives for the rest of this year! Let's build it together! 🚀👩🏻‍🚀👩🏼‍🚀👨🏼‍🚀

\- [Madelena], [JLo], & [Laura]

[Madelena]: https://github.com/Madelena
[JLo]: https://github.com/jlpouffier
[Laura]: https://github.com/laupalombi
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Register today for Community Day 2025]]></title>
    <link href="https://ivangrod.github.io/needlehack-blog/blog/2025/04/24/community-day/"/>
    <updated>2025-04-24T00:00:01+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://ivangrod.github.io/needlehack-blog/blog/2025/04/24/community-day</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<img src='/images/blog/2025-04-community-day/art.png' style='border: 0;box-shadow: none;' alt="Community Day - May 24th" style='border: 0;box-shadow: none;'>

Our first **Home Assistant Community Day** will be on **May 24th** this year 🎉, and with a month to go, here is all the information you need to take part.

The community will be leading meetups across the globe, so find your nearest event and **[register now](https://lu.ma/haday2025)**! They're all free and will be full of smart people with smart homes. If you don't see your city on this list, we're encouraging the community to host their own meetups, so keep reading to learn more.

## Our biggest party yet

I'm sure you're all wondering, "*Missy, what is a Community Day?*". In its simplest form, it's a single day in which community members around the world set up local meetups with each other. That leaves a lot open, though. *Where do you sign up? How do you host your own meetup? How many people should show up? Where's the best place to hold a meetup?* ...that's a lot of questions! 😳 Luckily, I have all the answers 😉.

<!--more-->

### Locations and registering to attend

To coordinate all these meetups, we are using Luma, a site focused on tech meetups. All the current events can be found below or on our [Home Assistant Community Day](https://lu.ma/haday2025) calendar.

<iframe
  data-src="https://lu.ma/embed/calendar/cal-QXZXEJrvB3UaI63/events?lt=light"
  width="100%"
  height="600"
  frameborder="0"
  style="border: 1px solid #bfcbda88; border-radius: 4px;"
  allowfullscreen=""
  aria-hidden="false"
  tabindex="0"
></iframe>

All Community Day events are free, so **[register before spaces run out!](https://lu.ma/haday2025)** (No worries, there are waitlists!). We also have people who work full-time on Home Assistant attending these events. To find out who you can meet, head over to Luma 😎!

### Host your own

***Is your city, country, or continent not on the list*** ⁉️ Time to take matters into your own hands, and create your own meetup.

<p class="img"><img src='/images/blog/2025-04-community-day/event.png' alt="Example event"/>Example event page for our London meetup 💂‍♂️🇬🇧</p>

Using Luma, [create an account](https://lu.ma/signin), and navigate to our [Home Assistant Community Day](https://lu.ma/haday2025) event page, select **Submit Event > Create New Event** (the button is above the calendar on the right). Don't stress if you don't have a venue yet---you can add it later! So people know you're part of the worldwide party, we've created an [invite graphic](https://drive.google.com/drive/u/0/folders/1xnAIVvsekX1tmfE60f0qrHOoIFK9Cw_R) you can set as the event image. Make sure you follow this checklist when you create your event:

✅ **Event Name** = "(city name) meetup"\
✅ **Time zone** = your local time\
✅ **Date** = Saturday, May 24\
✅ **Time** = your choosing! (4 hours max)\
✅ **Add Event Location** = your city (or venue once you have one)\
✅ **Capacity** = 50 max (less if the venue is smaller), and toggle the Waitlist on\
✅ **Hosts** = Add me (Missy Quarry - missy.quarry@openhomefoundation.org) as a host of the event so I can make sure it appears in the main event calendar

Click **Create Event** once you've followed that checklist, then come let everyone know in the Home Assistant Community Day [meetup thread on Discord](https://discord.com/channels/330944238910963714/1364989531069091920) or the [Social section of the Community forum](https://community.home-assistant.io/c/social/)! 🎉

***Capacity:*** If you're wondering why we capped the capacity at 50, this is mostly to ensure that hosts don't feel overwhelmed with finding a venue big enough. Also, that's the average number of attendees who have registered for the last couple of events. You may have more people who want to attend your event - that's where the waitlist comes in handy. 👏🏻

***Location:*** This will depend on the host, but we highly encourage hosts to check out local venues like cafes, community spaces, or bars. Please make sure the venue agrees to you hosting the event there and that it's an accommodating and welcoming place for everyone in our community. Consider accessibility and the facilities required for large groups (access to transport, food, drink, and washrooms)---this is also why we ask that people not host at their homes. Feel free to consider other public spaces, for instance, I pulled some strings at Microsoft for a cool space on campus to host the [Redmond meetup](https://lu.ma/qb0hhhkm). Just remember, the venue fees are up to the host to pay.

***What to provide/organize:*** These are free events, and hosts are not obligated to provide anything but good conversation. Keep it simple---this is just a chance for people to meet and chat.

***Keep attendees informed:***  You can always talk it out with your registered attendees via Luma---hosts will have the ability to "*Send a Blast*" out to their attendees. Also, the Community Day thread on Discord will be a great way to hook up with attendees on that platform. We'll promote these events on the Home Assistant socials, to ensure we reach the whole community.

***Clashes:***  If two or more events are requested in the same city, we'll link up hosts so they can organize things together.

***Have more questions for me?*** Send me a message on Discord ([@adorablecyborg](https://discord.com/users/303933403303247872)) or [email](mailto:missy@openhomefoundation.org?subject=Community%20Day%202025)--- I'm absolutely happy to help you out where I can! 😌

## See you soon

Our team has been meeting the community all over the world, and y'all never cease to amaze me. People are doing really cool stuff with Home Assistant, and you'll leave meetups with new automation ideas, cool DIY plans, and maybe even some new friends. Honestly, if you're like me, every one of my family members are sick of hearing about my smart home, it's time to meet some people who only want to talk about that! 🤝

If you can't make it on  May 24th, don't fret---there'll be a Community Day next year! Although Community Day will be special, you can always get on the Home Assistant community [meetup channel](https://discord.com/channels/330944238910963714/1325926382575816725) in Discord or the [Social section of the forum](https://community.home-assistant.io/c/social/) to set up group meetups throughout the year. 😊

I can't wait to see all the events added and how many people register for these meetups! 🤩 I'll share more information as the day approaches, including how you can share your meetup photo 📸, which we'll feature on our channels. See you on the socials!
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
