<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Video | Home Assistant]]></title>
  <link href="https://ivangrod.github.io/needlehack-blog/blog/categories/video/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://ivangrod.github.io/needlehack-blog/"/>
  <updated>2025-09-23T16:44:51+00:00</updated>
  <id>https://ivangrod.github.io/needlehack-blog/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Home Assistant]]></name>
    
  </author>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Energy management research using Home Assistant]]></title>
    <link href="https://ivangrod.github.io/needlehack-blog/blog/2021/12/28/northeastern-university-home-energy-management/"/>
    <updated>2021-12-28T00:01:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://ivangrod.github.io/needlehack-blog/blog/2021/12/28/northeastern-university-home-energy-management</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[Two weeks ago we hosted the [State of the Open Home](/state-of-the-open-home/). It included a presentation by [Prof. Michael Kane](https://coe.northeastern.edu/people/kane-michael/) and [Maharsi Pathak](https://www.linkedin.com/in/maharshi-pathak-) from the department of Civil and Environmental Engineering at [Northeastern University](https://www.northeastern.edu/).

They presented about their research into lowering grid demand by reducing thermostat temperatures. They want to learn when and why a reduced temperature is too uncomfortable causing tenants to become thermally frustrated and reverting the reduction.

<lite-youtube videoid="6ZMXE5PXPqU" videotitle="State of the Open Home 2021" videoStartAt="8042" posterquality="maxresdefault"></lite-youtube>

With Home Assistant we want every home to be about [privacy, choice and sustainability](/blog/2021/12/23/the-open-home/) and it's how we built Home Assistant. Because we believe in choice, all data in Home Assistant is accessible and one can extend or built on top of our platform.

This architecture made it possible for Prof. Kane to create a custom version of Home Assistant for his research that gathers data about all devices, surveys users based on changes to devices and exports all this data back to their research lab. For this they leverage device integrations, added a custom survey feature to the UI and push notifications from the Home Assistant companion app to draw the user's attention to the surveys.

But what makes me extra happy is that their research is focusing on home energy management. This has been a feature we added to Home Assistant in 2020 as [our way to help tackle the climate crisis](/blog/2021/08/04/home-energy-management/). It makes me proud to see that we are able to help researchers do their work and we hope to see more of this. We're also looking forward to collaborating with Prof. Kane on using his research to improve Home Assistant.

![Overview of their deployment](/images/blog/2021-12-northeastern-university/overview.png)
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Open Home]]></title>
    <link href="https://ivangrod.github.io/needlehack-blog/blog/2021/12/23/the-open-home/"/>
    <updated>2021-12-23T00:01:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://ivangrod.github.io/needlehack-blog/blog/2021/12/23/the-open-home</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<img src='/images/blog/2021-12-open-home/header.png' style='box-shadow:none;border:0'>

The Open Home is our vision for the smart home. It defines the values that we put at the heart of every decision we make at Home Assistant. It's woven into our architecture, licensing, community and everything else.

The Open Home is about **privacy**, **choice** and **sustainability**.

_The original vision used "durability" instead of "sustainability". This value was changed as [part of our 10 year anniversary](https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=EmLV6lJLzSU&t=3651s)._

_If you prefer video, skip [to the end](#state-of-the-open-home)._

## Privacy

Your home should be your safe space. A place where you can be your true self without having to bother about what the world thinks of you. A place where you don't need to act differently to avoid an algorithm categorizing your behavior.

**Privacy** for the Open Home means that devices need to work locally. No one else needs to know if you turn on a light bulb or change the thermostat.

It is okay for a product to offer a cloud connection, but it should be extra and opt-in.

## Choice

Devices in your home gather data about itself and their surroundings. Your data. Vendors shouldn't be able to limit your access to your data or limit the interoperability of your devices with the rest of your smart home.

**Choice** for the Open Home means that devices need to make the gathered data available through local APIs. This avoids vendor lock-in and allows users to create their own smart home with devices from different manufacturers.

## Sustainability

Humans emit CO<sub>2</sub> into the atmosphere, causing the climate to change and the world to heat up. One way we can all help with this is to ensure that our individual energy and waste footprint is as small as possible. Our homes represent a substantial part of this.

For the Open Home, longevity of a device should not be an afterthought. If there is one thing that technology firms are very good at, it is launching new products. However, maintaining the products and making sure they keep working is an afterthought for most. The result is that vendors can decide to no longer support your device, crippling it's features or even prevent it from working at all.

As we install more and more devices in our home, sustainability is becoming more and more important. We shouldn't have to buy everything new every couple of years because the manufacturer decided to move on.

**Sustainability** for the Open Home means that devices are designed and built to keep working and use as little energy as possible. Not just this year, but for the next decade. If they outlive their original purpose, they should be able to be reused or repurposed for something else.

## State of the Open Home

At the State of the Open Home, we presented our vision and how we, together with our friends from open source and academia, are working towards achieving it.

<lite-youtube videoid="6ZMXE5PXPqU" videotitle="State of the Open Home 2021" videoStartAt="512" posterquality="maxresdefault"></lite-youtube>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Demo: Genie, privacy-preserving virtual assistant by Stanford]]></title>
    <link href="https://ivangrod.github.io/needlehack-blog/blog/2021/12/21/stanford-genie/"/>
    <updated>2021-12-21T00:01:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://ivangrod.github.io/needlehack-blog/blog/2021/12/21/stanford-genie</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[Last week we hosted the [State of the Open Home](/state-of-the-open-home/) and it included a demo of [Genie](https://genie.stanford.edu).

Genie is an open, privacy-preserving virtual assistant by [Stanford OVAL](https://oval.cs.stanford.edu/). During the impressive demo they showed it's latest capabilities. The demos run on a Baidu speaker with custom firmware and on a Pi Zero. In both cases it connects to the Genie server running as an official Home Assistant add-on to do it's magic.

<lite-youtube videoid="6ZMXE5PXPqU" videotitle="State of the Open Home 2021" videoStartAt="9691" posterquality="maxresdefault"></lite-youtube>

Genie is the successor to the Almond project. With the help of various grants and sponsors Stanford is working on making Genie ready for general use.

If you want to learn more, check out the Genie [website](https://genie.stanford.edu) and the [getting started guide](https://wiki.genie.stanford.edu/getting-started/installation-guide) on how to make your own. To get in touch with other Genie users and their dev team, check their [Discord](https://discord.gg/anthtR4)
 or [community forums](https://community.almond.stanford.edu/).

If you end up using Genie at home, don't forget to share the love and share your demo's and tutorials.

![Genie logo](/images/blog/2021-12-stanford-genie/social.png)
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[State of the Union]]></title>
    <link href="https://ivangrod.github.io/needlehack-blog/blog/2018/11/16/state-of-the-union/"/>
    <updated>2018-11-16T00:01:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://ivangrod.github.io/needlehack-blog/blog/2018/11/16/state-of-the-union</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p class='img'>
  <img src='/images/blog/2018-11-state-of-the-union/share-the-love.jpg' alt='Photo of Paulus Schoutsen presenting the state of the union.'>
</p>

Last Wednesday, November 14, we had a meetup in Amsterdam hosted by <a href='https://www.ing.nl'>ING</a>. Over 80 Home Assistant enthusiasts gathered to hear me, Paulus Schoutsen, the founder of Home Assistant, speak. I talked about how Home Assistant got started, what makes Home Assistant so successful (community!) and what we're working towards.

<div class='videoWrapper'>
<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/egcOCWIh9jQ" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div>

Special thanks to:

 - Jeroen Joosse for the initiative and organizing
 - Erik-Jan Riemers for co-organizing and making it this big
 - ING for hosting the event
 - Franck Nijhof for providing the Hass.io demos
 - Klaas Schoute for providing the TensorFlow demos
 - Frank Kuiper for editing the presentation video

More photos after the click.

<!--more-->

<p class='img'>
  <img src='/images/blog/2018-11-state-of-the-union/chatter.jpg' alt='Crowd talking Home Assistant'>
  Crowd talking Home Assistant
</p>

<p class='img'>
  <img src='/images/blog/2018-11-state-of-the-union/frenck-hassio.jpg' alt='Frenck showing all the ins and outs of Hass.io'>
  Frenck showing all the ins and outs of Hass.io
</p>

<p class='img'>
  <img src='/images/blog/2018-11-state-of-the-union/zwave-table.jpg' alt='The Z-Wave table'>
  The Z-Wave table
</p>

<p class='img'>
  <img src='/images/blog/2018-11-state-of-the-union/presentation-selfie.jpg' alt='Presentation selfie!'>
  Presentation selfie!
</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Home Assistant at PyCon 2016]]></title>
    <link href="https://ivangrod.github.io/needlehack-blog/blog/2016/06/13/home-assistant-at-pycon-2016/"/>
    <updated>2016-06-13T01:06:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://ivangrod.github.io/needlehack-blog/blog/2016/06/13/home-assistant-at-pycon-2016</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[It's been already almost two weeks ago that a few of the Home Assistant developers headed towards Portland for [PyCon 2016] - the conference about everything Python. We were there to learn all the nifty tricks to make our code better but most of all, to talk Home Automation.

<p class='img'>
  <img src='/images/blog/2016-06-pycon/crew.jpg' alt='Home Assistant developers' />
  Couple of Home Assistant devs. Left to right: [Paulus (@balloob)], [Alex (@infamy)], [Ryan (@rmkraus)].
</p>

On Monday I (Paulus) gave a presentation about Home Assistant to an audience of over 400 people! It was a bit scary at first but after a couple of minutes it went all great including some great questions afterwards. Slides can be found [here][slides] and the talk is embedded right below:

<div class='videoWrapper'>
<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/UhccJacWhdM" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div>

One of the things that really impressed me was the amount of people that approached us to tell how they love Home Assistant, how it has replaced their previous solution, how they enjoyed contributing to Home Assistant and how helpful our community is. It makes me proud of Home Assistant and especially our community.

<!--more-->
PyCon has a few great concepts that I haven't seen at other conferences: open spaces and sprints. Open spaces give anyone the opportunity to get a room and host a session for an hour to talk about any topic. Sprints happen after the conference part of PyCon is over. For four days there are rooms available for participants to get together and hack on their favorite open source projects.

My talk had limited time for Q&A so open spaces offered a great opportunity to get all pending questions answered and connect with the commmunity. There was more interest after the first day so we ended up hosting another open space on the second day.

<blockquote markdown="0" class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"><p lang="en" dir="ltr"><a href="https://twitter.com/anschoen">@anschoen</a> <a href="https://twitter.com/home_assistant">@home_assistant</a> I&#39;m located in Detroit. I could facilitate a workshop. What are we talking (group, potential dates, etc)?</p>&mdash; Jonathan Baginski (@patchedsoul) <a href="https://twitter.com/jbags81/status/739057625636167680">June 4, 2016</a></blockquote>

We've had such positive reception on our open spaces that [Jonathan Baginski][@patchedsoul] decided to repeat it online. We will be hosting a free online webinar [Home Assistant Support 101 - Getting around in Home Assistant][webinar] later this month. Make sure to RSVP.

After the conference part of PyCon was over we spent one extra day to host a Home Assistant sprint. This allowed us to help people get started with hacking on Home Assistant which lead to some great contributions.

<p class='img'>
  <img src='/images/blog/2016-06-pycon/sprint.jpg' alt='Home Assistant sprint group photo' />
  Home Assistant sprint group photo.
</p>

I've had a really great time at PyCon. It was awesome to meet everyone in person and I hope to see many of you next year!

[PyCon 2016]: https://us.pycon.org/2016/
[Paulus (@balloob)]: https://github.com/balloob/
[Alex (@infamy)]: https://github.com/infamy/
[Ryan (@rmkraus)]: https://github.com/rmkraus/
[@patchedsoul]: https://github.com/patchedsoul/
[slides]: https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/1F1pGOoSf0dD79Dl5dgys0ll7xiuIA4XiQeNeJ-xlqMg/edit
[webinar]: https://www.eventbrite.com/e/home-assistant-support-101-getting-around-in-home-assistant-tickets-25943868810
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
