<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Roadmap | Home Assistant]]></title>
  <link href="https://ivangrod.github.io/blog/categories/roadmap/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://ivangrod.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2025-09-23T17:02:13+00:00</updated>
  <id>https://ivangrod.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Home Assistant]]></name>
    
  </author>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Roadmap 2025: A Truly Smart Home through Collective Intelligence]]></title>
    <link href="https://ivangrod.github.io/blog/2025/05/09/roadmap-2025h1/"/>
    <updated>2025-05-09T00:00:01+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://ivangrod.github.io/blog/2025/05/09/roadmap-2025h1</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<img alt="Devices, Automations, Dashboards, Voice & Music, Frontend" src="/needlehack-blog/images/blog/2025-05-roadmap-2025h1/roadmap-2025-cover.png" class='no-shadow'/>
<p>It’s been a year since we launched <a href="/blog/2024/06/12/roadmap-2024h1/">our first roadmap</a> for Home Assistant, which means it’s time to launch this year’s first update! In 2025, we’re building on our direction to make Home Assistant easier to use for everyone in your household, and taking it to the next level by making smart homes more intuitive, proactive, and user-friendly. 🚀</p>
<p>This centers on helping Home Assistant understand devices in their context, and cataloging every device that works with Home Assistant through a new project, Device Database. And we will do this the Home Assistant way — through the power of our community and our collective intelligence. (…but that’s not all! The roadmap also covers many product areas we are aiming to work on from automation to voice to dashboard <a href="#and-thats-not-all-for-this-year">and more</a>!)</p>
<p>If you’re new to our roadmaps or curious about how they guide the development of Home Assistant, be sure to check out <a href="/blog/2024/06/12/roadmap-introduction/">our introduction</a> to Home Assistant roadmaps. As always, your feedback is incredibly valuable, so please give us your thoughts in the comments.</p>
<!-- TOC -->
<ul>
<li><a href="#one-year-on-the-road">One year on the road</a></li>
<li><a href="#the-smart-home-administrator-as-an-inventor">The smart home administrator as an inventor</a></li>
<li><a href="#from-shared-wisdom-to-collective-intelligence">From shared wisdom to collective intelligence</a></li>
<li><a href="#putting-devices-in-context">Putting Devices in Context</a></li>
<li><a href="#introducing-the-device-database">Introducing the Device Database</a></li>
<li><a href="#and-thats-not-all-for-this-year">And that’s not all for this year!</a></li>
<li><a href="#laying-the-groundwork-for-a-truly-smart-home">Laying the Groundwork for a Truly Smart Home</a></li>
</ul>
<!-- /TOC -->
<!--more-->
<h2>One year on the road</h2>
<p>Last year, we introduced <a href="/blog/2024/06/12/roadmap-2024h1/">our very first roadmap</a>—and it wasn’t just plans on paper. It marked a new chapter for Home Assistant: one where we made our direction clear, set ambitious goals, and invited the whole community along for the ride.</p>
<p>In <a href="/blog/2024/06/12/roadmap-2024h1/">2024</a>, we focused on building a smart home that has a high Home Approval Factor: helping both the maintainer and residents of the smart home unlock more value from Home Assistant without needing to be an expert. This was done by improving the touchpoints that all members of the household will interact with, such as automations, dashboards, and voice interactions, while maintaining the power and depth of the platform for our power users and admins.</p>
<p>The real challenge lay in building a roadmap from scratch. That meant not only poring through and prioritizing every single feature request, but also increasing transparency and building trust in the roadmap within our organization and our community as a beacon that can help guide the development of the project. Thanks to the feedback, energy, and contributions from our global community, we’ve made huge strides. In the past year, we tackled some of the biggest pain points, such as drag-and-drop dashboard improvements, automation grouping, standard voice assistant hardware, better automated backups, and more.</p>
<p>Now, in 2025, we are ready to lay the groundwork for the next big step forward: Making Home Assistant <em>truly smart</em> through our collective effort and intelligence.</p>
<h2>The smart home administrator as an inventor</h2>
<p>Home Approval Factor means that a successful smart home isn’t just great for the person who set it up, but for everyone who lives there. Whether it’s your partner, kids, or roommates, we want Home Assistant to feel intuitive and supportive for the whole household.</p>
<p>In some ways, being a smart home administrator is like being an inventor (or, as we would say, a product manager). To be a great inventor, you need to understand your users. What are their needs? What solutions can you invent to solve their problems? How do you know you solved their problems? Can you improve upon the solution?</p>
<p>Home Assistant provides all the building blocks for our administrators to build whatever they want and let their imaginations run wild, and better yet, it’s easier than ever with the improvements we made last year! However, that’s also the curse of a blank slate. Inventing fun and hyper-personalized solutions for niche problems is a major appeal of Home Assistant, but sometimes, maintenance of a smart home can be a chore — not every single problem requires reinventing the wheel.</p>
<p>The reality today is that, according to our <a href="/blog/2025/04/16/state-of-the-open-home-recap/#research">community survey</a>, just 46% of partners and only 27% of children of long-time Home Assistant users are directly interacting with Home Assistant. That’s a big gap, and it highlights a broader challenge: Even the most experienced smart home administrators don’t always have the complete picture of their household’s needs. They may not realize what would help until something goes wrong. And it’s unreasonable to expect everyone to be an expert in everything — from automations to dashboards to onboarding new users.</p>
<h2>From shared wisdom to collective intelligence</h2>
<p class='img'><img alt="wisdom spread across social, chats, and videos" src="/needlehack-blog/images/blog/2025-05-roadmap-2025h1/shared-wisdom.jpg"/></p>
<p>Right now, if a smart home admin wants to improve their setup, they have to go hunting—through our community forums, GitHub repos, Reddit threads, YouTube videos, Discord chats… you name it—trying to find tips and tricks that apply to their specific case. You share incredible wisdom with each other every day, but much of it is scattered, short-lived, or hard to apply without lots of customization.</p>
<p>We believe it’s time for a smarter system.</p>
<p>What if Home Assistant could learn from our community’s best ideas and use that knowledge to proactively suggest improvements? What if it could guide users based on what others have done in similar situations? That’s the vision we’re working toward: using collective intelligence to power a truly smart home.</p>
<p class='img'><img alt="organized shared wisdom is collective intelligence" src="/needlehack-blog/images/blog/2025-05-roadmap-2025h1/collective-intelligence.jpg"/></p>
<p>To get there, Home Assistant needs to <em>understand</em> what’s in the home. Inside each home, there are the people, the spaces, and the devices. This year, we will start with helping Home Assistant understand devices in terms of (1) <strong>context</strong>: what each device is and how it is used, and (2) <strong>information</strong>: every device that works with Home Assistant and how it is supported.</p>
<h2>Putting Devices in Context</h2>
<p>Today, most devices in Home Assistant show up as a bundle of entities: a temperature sensor here, a switch there. This is by design — we want to provide the ultimate flexibility in configuring your system, and will continue to do so. However, it is not without disadvantages.</p>
<p class='img'><img alt="Fridge as a series of entities" src="/needlehack-blog/images/blog/2025-05-roadmap-2025h1/devices-without-context.jpg"/></p>
<p>For example, we don’t always know that those entities together form, say, a fridge, which is essentially a mini house of its own: It may have temperature sensors, a door sensor, a light, and so on, but Home Assistant cannot assume them as any other sensors or lights within a room. Without that context, Home Assistant can’t do much beyond letting users build their own dashboards and automations from scratch.</p>
<p>As you add more devices, entities pile up, and Home Assistant starts to lose the thread of what’s actually in the home. Your smart home should become more powerful as you add more devices, but at the cost of the difficulty of maintaining them also increasing exponentially.</p>
<p>When we <strong>put devices in context</strong>, everything changes. A fridge becomes more than a list of entities — it becomes an actual device that can have a dedicated dashboard, default automations, and contextual voice commands.</p>
<p class='img'><img alt="Dashboards, Automation and Voice in context" src="/needlehack-blog/images/blog/2025-05-roadmap-2025h1/device-context.jpg"/></p>
<p>Here’s how context unlocks a more streamlined experience across the platform:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Voice:</strong> Assist can currently source the right sensor if it knows the area of the device. In the future, we can also intelligently exclude irrelevant sensors from a voice query. For example, “What’s the temperature in the kitchen?” shouldn’t return the freezer’s internal temperature.</li>
<li><strong>Dashboards:</strong> Integrations can provide customized cards and dashboards right from the start, providing a much more streamlined experience. For example, we can provide a fridge dashboard. It works with other devices, too. Imagine a car dashboard or a 3D printer dashboard.</li>
<li><strong>Automations:</strong> By understanding what devices a user has and how they are commonly used, we can intelligently suggest automations created by our community. For example, “fridge door left open” or “fridge water leakage” alerts can be provided without building them manually from scratch.</li>
</ul>
<p>This will be a core architectural change that will be proposed and discussed in the coming months. We’re building on what our contributors already share in integrations: knowledge about how devices are structured and how they should behave. My hope is that this will provide the framework for our contributors to contribute dashboards and automation blueprints to our code in exciting new ways.</p>
<h2>Introducing the Device Database</h2>
<p>To make all this work, we also need a centralized, structured place to store and share device knowledge. That’s where the Device Database—a brand new project from the Open Home Foundation—comes in.</p>
<p>Think of it as a source of truth created, curated, and validated by the community. A place where we gather everything from metadata (like power usage or infrared codes) to factual information (setup instructions such as how to add or reset a device) to real-world setup insights and community creations (such as automation examples). It will contain information users intentionally submit to the database, nothing will be collected automatically without your explicit consent.</p>
<p>It’s more than just having all device documentation in one place. We want to universalize all our collective experiences about devices in one place, which is more accessible, centralized, and structured than online websites and chat rooms.</p>
<p>With the Device Database, users both old and new can easily make well-informed choices and pick the best Home Assistant-compatible devices for them based on real usage experiences, allowing them to easily make decisions based on open home values — privacy, choice, and sustainability.</p>
<p>The data will be used and cross-referenced in Home Assistant and other Open Home Foundation projects, and acts as the backbone of their integrations. For example, a future infrared integration can hypothetically benefit from having access to readily available infrared codes from the database.</p>
<p class='img'><img alt="Protocols, device database, feeding choice" src="/needlehack-blog/images/blog/2025-05-roadmap-2025h1/working-together.png"/></p>
<p>This isn’t something we can build alone. We’re relying on the strength of our global community to turn this vision into reality, and we’re backing it up with our infrastructure, engineering efforts, and partnerships:</p>
<ul>
<li>The <a href="https://www.openhomefoundation.org/">Open Home Foundation</a> is here to provide the framework to help us collect and collaborate on knowledge easily and safely.</li>
<li>We’re working with <a href="https://www.nabucasa.com/">Nabu Casa</a>—our commercial partner—to create the most reliable hardware antennas that support more open protocols, such as Z-Wave, Zigbee, Bluetooth, and more, to expand the Home Assistant ecosystem.</li>
<li>The <a href="https://works-with.home-assistant.io/">Works with Home Assistant program</a> is being strengthened to make it easier to find trusted, high-quality devices for the platform, as you may have witnessed with the <a href="/blog/categories/works-with-home-assistant/">numerous new partners</a> joining in the past few months.</li>
</ul>
<p>The result? A system where no admin has to figure everything out in isolation on their own. Home Assistant can suggest, guide, adapt, and point users in the right direction, by drawing from the collective intelligence of the community (instead of scraping user data involuntarily like what Big Tech does).</p>
<h2>And that’s not all for this year!</h2>
<p class='img'><img alt="Devices, Automations, Dashboards, Voice & Music, Frontend" src="/needlehack-blog/images/blog/2025-05-roadmap-2025h1/roadmap-2025.png"/></p>
<p>While device context and the Device Database are the major themes of this year’s roadmap, it doesn’t mean that we are dropping everything else that does not fit. We’re continuing work on other parts of the product experience:</p>
<ul>
<li>A complete revamp of our automation triggers and conditions to make them both easier to use and more powerful.</li>
<li>A navigation and design system overhaul to improve feature discovery.</li>
<li>Continued improvements to make dashboards easier to use out of the box, including a new default dashboard and more.</li>
<li>Enhanced privacy controls for users, guests, and public access (Yes, I am aware of that.)</li>
<li>Easier setup for Music Assistant.</li>
<li>Make Assist more conversational, such as the ability to confirm and clarify a query.</li>
<li>Continued explorations in using LLMs to improve the overall user experience beyond voice.</li>
</ul>
<p>In the meantime, we are working on making our roadmap more publicly accessible, so that you can discuss and track our progress with us! Stay tuned.</p>
<h2>Laying the Groundwork for a Truly Smart Home</h2>
<p>This roadmap isn’t about the flashy latest tech fad (what is it now anyway?) or abstract features. It’s about creating the enduring foundation to allow our community to build something greater than all of us together: a smart home platform that learns, grows, and adapts — with full respect for privacy, choice, and sustainability.</p>
<p>The central theme of the roadmap is that making Home Assistant smarter starts with understanding context, such as knowing what devices are and how they’re used, and we will use this collective intelligence to supercharge the main pillars of the user experience — automations, voice, and dashboards.</p>
<p>We’re making maintenance of a smart home easier, by making it less like a mandatory chore while still keeping the fun of tinkering (say, you wanna go wild on YAML), and by creating tools to help admins solve problems they don’t even know they have yet. We believe that, as our advanced users continue to tinker with their systems, their creations and discoveries will also benefit and elevate every user’s smart home.</p>
<p>We can’t wait to work on these initiatives for the rest of this year! Let’s build it together! 🚀👩🏻‍🚀👩🏼‍🚀👨🏼‍🚀</p>
<p>- <a href="https://github.com/Madelena">Madelena</a>, <a href="https://github.com/jlpouffier">JLo</a>, &amp; <a href="https://github.com/laupalombi">Laura</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Roadmap 2024 Year-end Update: Full steam ahead!]]></title>
    <link href="https://ivangrod.github.io/blog/2024/11/15/roadmap-2024h2/"/>
    <updated>2024-11-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://ivangrod.github.io/blog/2024/11/15/roadmap-2024h2</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src='/images/blog/2024-11-roadmap-2024h2/ha-roadmap-2024h2.png' class='no-shadow' alt='Roadmap 2024 H2 diagram, showing the priorities as a table'/></p>
<p><strong>TL;DR</strong> We are making great progress on our roadmap, and moving forward onto the next priorities on the roadmap. 🚂🚃🚃🚃🚃🚃🚃🚃🚃</p>
<p>As <a href="/blog/2024/06/12/roadmap-introduction/">we had previously mentioned</a>, the goal of the roadmap is to provide a North Star for all of our product initiatives to follow in a coherent and consistent direction. At the <a href="/blog/2024/04/24/state-of-the-open-home-2024/">State of the Open Home</a> in April this year, we introduced to our community <a href="/blog/2024/06/12/roadmap-2024h1/">our first roadmap</a>. We intend to keep our community informed every half year, and this is our first update to our public roadmap.</p>
<p>We are happy to report that we have made good progress on the product initiatives on our roadmap so far, thanks to our core maintainers along with the help of the team at <a href="https://nabucasa.com">Nabu Casa</a>, the commercial partner of the <a href="https://www.openhomefoundation.org">Open Home Foundation</a>. Most of the product initiatives in the 2024 roadmap have matured according to plan, and now the team has begun to focus on the ones that we had planned for next.</p>
<p>- <a href="https://github.com/Madelena">Madelena</a> &amp; <a href="https://github.com/jlpouffier">JLo</a></p>
<!--more-->
<ul>
<li><a href="#home-assistant-a-home-approved-smart-home">Home Assistant: “A Home-Approved Smart Home”</a>
<ul>
<li><a href="#automations">Automations</a>
<ul>
<li><a href="#in-good-shape-make-automations-easier-to-organize">In good shape: Make automations easier to organize</a></li>
<li><a href="#newly-in-progress-make-automations-easier-to-create">Newly in progress: Make automations easier to create</a></li>
<li><a href="#later-priority-make-blueprints-easier-to-use">Later priority: Make blueprints easier to use</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="#dashboards">Dashboards</a>
<ul>
<li><a href="#in-good-shape-make-customization-of-dashboards-easy-and-intuitive">In good shape: Make customization of dashboards easy and intuitive</a></li>
<li><a href="#newly-in-progress-make-default-dashboards-more-useful-and-relevant">Newly in progress: Make default dashboards more useful and relevant</a></li>
<li><a href="#next-priority-improve-privacy-in-user-guest-and-public-access">Next priority: Improve privacy in user, guest, and public access</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="#voice-assistants">Voice Assistants</a>
<ul>
<li><a href="#in-good-shape-improve-assist-capabilities-out-of-the-box">In good shape: Improve Assist capabilities out of the box</a></li>
<li><a href="#in-progress-make-assist-easier-to-start-with">In progress: Make Assist easier to start with</a></li>
<li><a href="#later-priority-make-assist-more-conversational">Later priority: Make Assist more conversational</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="#research">Research</a>
<ul>
<li><a href="#in-good-shape-build-local-llm-infrastructure">In good shape: Build local LLM infrastructure</a></li>
<li><a href="#in-progress-investigate-on-privacy">In progress: Investigate on privacy</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="#home-assistant-cloud">Home Assistant Cloud</a></li>
<li><a href="#open-protocols">Open Protocols</a>
<ul>
<li><a href="#z-wave">Z-Wave</a></li>
<li><a href="#matter">Matter</a></li>
<li><a href="#zigbee">Zigbee</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="#whats-next">What’s next?</a></li>
</ul>
<h2>Home Assistant: “A Home-Approved Smart Home”</h2>
<p>The theme of the Home Assistant roadmap is to improve the <a href="https://newsletter.openhomefoundation.org/open-home-approval-factor/">Home Approval Factor</a> of our platform, ensuring the adoption of Home Assistant by other household members within a smart home.</p>
<p>This can be done by improving the touchpoints that all members of the household will interact with, such as <a href="#automations">automations</a>, <a href="#dashboards">dashboards</a>, and <a href="#voice-assistants">voice assistants</a>, while maintaining the power and depth of the platform for our power users and admins. Our plan is categorized into the following product areas:</p>
<h3>Automations</h3>
<h4>In good shape: Make automations easier to organize</h4>
<p>For a long time, the ability to organize automation was at the top of our feature requests. Therefore, organizing automations was our first focus on the automation product area.</p>
<p>We gave users the ability to categorize automations, which makes the process of managing, editing, debugging, and searching automations much simpler. The categories are up to the users to define. For instance, I personally created categories per functionality such as “Smart Heating” or “Smart Cleaning”, and I particularly like my “Tests” categories where I keep all the automations that are currently being tested in my home.</p>
<p><img src="/images/blog/2024-04/filter-panel.png" alt="Screenshot of Automations settings with filter panel" /></p>
<p>On top of categories, users can now attach labels to automations, just like any other entity found in Home Assistant. Labels can be used to filter the automation list further, but what I am most interested in is the automation capabilities of the labels themselves. I saw some great ideas in the community, one of them that struck me was the idea to label some automation as “Not Guest Friendly” and deactivate them when a guest mode was activated. It’s nice to see labels as a tool to automate everything, even your automations themselves. 😀</p>
<p>All in all, Home Assistant truly made automations easier to organize in the past 6 months. We could still work on that, no opportunity is ever really done, but for the time being, we are considering this one done so that we can focus on bigger problems.</p>
<h4>Newly in progress: Make automations easier to create</h4>
<p>Automations are one of the cornerstones of Home Assistant, but it’s not an easy task to create them, especially if you are just starting out. There are a dozen things to know before you start and a dozen things to learn along the way.</p>
<img class="no-shadow" src="/needlehack-blog/images/blog/2024-01/add-action-search.png" alt="Screenshot showing the new add action dialog utilizing the search function to find whatever you need.">
<p>Last year we redesigned our action picker and replaced a single option with an obscure name, <strong>“Call Service”</strong>, with hundreds of neatly categorized entries that we called <strong>“Actions”</strong>. This improved the automation creation process by quite a margin.</p>
<p>Today, the automation editor feels like it has progressed at two different speeds; our actions are easy to use, but our triggers and conditions are not. So we have begun bringing the same level of convenience that we previously brought to actions to our beloved triggers and conditions.</p>
<p>Our goal is to make our automation editor more approachable without losing what makes us unique: Its capabilities.</p>
<h4>Later priority: Make blueprints easier to use</h4>
<p>Blueprints are amazing, they represent what makes the Home Assistant community truly great: Sharing what you learned with others.</p>
<p>We are aware that using (and sharing) blueprints is not the most straightforward process today. For now, this is the next opportunity we want to tackle inside the automation stream.</p>
<h3>Dashboards</h3>
<h4>In good shape: Make customization of dashboards easy and intuitive</h4>
<p>With the stable release of the new Sections view layout in Home Assistant <a href="/blog/2024/11/06/release-202411/">2024.11</a>, our work on making customization of dashboards easier is now in good shape! The learning curve for creating nice dashboards has been vastly reduced, and we are seeing more and more people being interested in and being able to create high-quality dashboards that are usable for everyone in the household.</p>
<p class='img no-shadow'><img class="no-shadow" alt="Screenshots showing the conversion of a view in masonry into sections" src="/needlehack-blog/images/blog/2024-11/dashboard-conversion.png"/>Screenshots showing the conversion of a view in masonry into sections</p>
<p>Work will continue with the dashboard working group. The group is currently looking into standardizing the appearance of our default cards. <strong>Please <a href="/blog/2024/07/26/dashboard-chapter-2/#process-how-can-we-work-together">reach out to us</a> if you are a frontend developer</strong> who would like to contribute and be part of the journey!</p>
<h4>Newly in progress: Make default dashboards more useful and relevant</h4>
<p>Now that we’ve made customization of dashboards easier than ever, what’s next? We understand that it can be intimidating for users when they are faced with a blank slate. Some may be full of ideas on how they would like to fill their dashboards up, but some would prefer if Home Assistant came with something useful out-of-the-box. Therefore, we are now looking into making dashboards easier, even if you don’t know how to create one.</p>
<p class='img'><img alt="Case studies of many dashboards of our users" src="/needlehack-blog/images/blog/2024-11-roadmap-2024h2/dashboard-casestudies.png"/>Case studies of many dashboards of our users</p>
<p>Over the past year, we have looked into dozens of case studies - dashboards created by many of you, from the most popular to the most pragmatic - and began to notice patterns in how our users organize their dashboards. Home Assistant is unique compared to other smart home platforms in that our dashboards are not just about controlling devices. After all, the perfect app is no app, as in, opening an app to control your light bulb is less convenient than simply flicking a light switch, or better yet, just automating it.</p>
<p>What we see our users have built instead are dashboards that help them keep track of information for their daily lives at a glance, and keep a birds-eye view of everything that is going on around their homes. For example, while you can automate Home Assistant to notify you when energy usage is too high, or you can ask Assist the current power usage, our dashboards shine at data visualization and its ability to tell you lots of information you need by just glancing at it.</p>
<p>Currently, our default dashboard simply dumps every single entity that a home has onto one page, making it wildly unmanageable as the smart home grows. While it can automatically group entities by areas, we have learned that areas are not the only way users look at their dashboard information. What we saw instead are dashboards that are specialized and focused on the functions of a home, such as energy usage, security and safety, and network status, on complex objects, such as a car and a 3D printer, or on information unrelated to the home itself, such as weather, neighborhood information, or even rocket launches. While we can simply show every entity by domain, we know we can make these function-focused dashboards much more useful by exposing insights by curating and juxtaposing information.</p>
<h4>Next priority: Improve privacy in user, guest, and public access</h4>
<p>The inability to fine-tune access to Home Assistant by guests or other members of the family has been a pain point requested by many of our users. We want to investigate ways to mitigate this while improving the privacy of the household. Our research on what privacy means to users will hopefully bring more clarity to this before we start working on it.</p>
<h3>Voice Assistants</h3>
<h4>In good shape: Improve Assist capabilities out of the box</h4>
<p>Assist, our private voice assistant, received a lot of love over the last 6 months. Our first focus was to improve its capabilities out of the box, without needing to tinker with it. We added a lot of features that were heavily requested by the community, features that bring us one step closer to feature parity with our non-private competitors.</p>
<p>We brought area awareness, which allows you to target devices in the same area without mentioning the area (like “Close the curtains” or “Turn off the lights”). We brought floor support, which allows you to target devices across areas on the same floor; very useful for homes with an open floor design (for example “Turn on all lights on the first floor”).</p>
<p class='img'><lite-youtube videoid="v3mNdTsX4J0" videotitle="Voice timers with countdown text and loading bar"></lite-youtube>Timers running on an S3 Box, with countdown text and a loading bar!</p>
<p>We implemented timers, allowing any voice assistant device to “ring” when a timer ends, including supporting the creation of multiple timers. You can also pause and resume them and add or remove time from them. You can combine commands with timers by giving a delayed command, allowing you to perform an action after a specific amount of time (like “Turn off the TV in 30 minutes)”.</p>
<p>We also brought the ability to control media via voice. Pausing or resuming them, controlling the volume, and going to the next track. This, combined with the area awareness capability mentioned above made for some really interesting short commands that work in a room with a TV playing or music streaming, such as “Pause”, “Resume” and “Next”.</p>
<p>Finally, our on-device wake word engine called microWakeWord became much faster and much better at recognizing wake words. This is the result of using real voice data in the training process to fine-tune the models. With <a href="https://ohf-voice.github.io/wake-word-collective/">Wake Word Collective</a>, you can now contribute by lending your voice to improve our community-driven, privacy-focused voice assistant! You can read more about it in <a href="/blog/2024/10/24/wake-word-collective/">this blog post</a>.</p>
<h4>In progress: Make Assist easier to start with</h4>
<p>So Assist is more capable, but what about getting started with Voice?</p>
<p>Voice is hard because it is a combination of great software and great hardware. Up until recently, we primarily focused on making the software experience great and relied on readily available hardware to power our voice assistants.</p>
<p class='img'><img alt="A teaser of our voice hardware" src="/needlehack-blog/images/blog/2024-11-roadmap-2024h2/voice-hardware-teaser.jpg"/>A teaser of our voice hardware</p>
<p>However, this is changing - over the past 6 months, we have built our own hardware! It will be the first voice assistant hardware built from the ground up to work with Home Assistant, fully open source (firmware and hardware), and it is going to be released <em>very soon</em>. It is truly the missing hardware piece to a more approachable voice experience in Home Assistant, and we cannot wait to see what you will build with it.</p>
<h4>Later priority: Make Assist more conversational</h4>
<p>The more functionality we add to Assist, the more we reach its transactional limitations. Indeed, today, an interaction is one way, from a user (issuing a command) to Assist (acting on that command). We would like to improve this, allowing more conversational interactions with Assist.</p>
<p>In the future, Assist will be able to ask for clarifications before fulfilling a command, such as requesting the duration of a timer if it was not part of the original command or asking for confirmation before processing critical actions, such as unlocking all doors. On top of that, we would like to allow the conversation to start from Assist, and not from the user, such as greeting someone when they enter a room.
This pairs very well with LLM-based conversation agents due to their ability to retain context, but we will make sure these types of complex interactions are also possible with our default conversation agent.</p>
<h3>Research</h3>
<h4>In good shape: Build local LLM infrastructure</h4>
<p>In the past six months, we’ve introduced support for LLM local tools and <a href="/blog/2024/08/07/release-20248/#control-home-assistant-using-ai-with-ollama">Ollama</a>, pushing our efforts to make AI more accessible and private for experimentation within Home Assistant. We’ve also dedicated significant effort to creating realistic benchmarks, focusing on natural, conversational use cases rather than edge cases. This approach lets us better understand performance and user experience in day-to-day interactions.</p>
<p>Our latest benchmark for local language models (LLMs) can be explored <a href="https://github.com/allenporter/home-assistant-datasets/tree/main/reports">here</a>, showcasing how models like qwen2.5 perform in realistic settings. With these insights, we’re continuing to refine LLM integrations and to ensure that LLMs can be depended upon for common use cases at home.</p>
<img src='/images/blog/2024-06-voice-chapter-7/voice-script.png' alt="Exposing voice scripts to Assist in Home Assistant Voice settings" class='no-shadow'>
<p>You can now expand LLM capabilities by <a href="/blog/2024/07/03/release-20247/#expand-an-llm-using-your-scripts">allowing them access to your scripts</a>. This feature lets you precisely control what the LLM does in specific situations, while still benefiting from the flexibility and natural language processing that AIs excel at.</p>
<h4>In progress: Investigate on privacy</h4>
<p>Since our last roadmap update, we have expanded the product and design team working on the Home Assistant project, and we have hired our first ever dedicated user researcher!</p>
<p>While we are ramping up our user research pipeline, we have started working on investigating what privacy means to our users. Of the three Open Home values, privacy, choice, and sustainability, while we have a pretty solid understanding of choice and some understanding of sustainability, the idea of privacy can benefit from more clarity. We have interviewed a handful of users on this topic recently, and we can’t wait to show you what we have found.</p>
<h2>Home Assistant Cloud</h2>
<p>Home Assistant Cloud, powered by our commercial partner Nabu Casa brings, to the many, the hard-to-reach features of Home Assistant usually reserved for power users with expensive hardware at home, with no compromise on privacy.</p>
<p>In recent months, the Nabu Casa team has been hard at work in bringing peace of mind to using Home Assistant. For the cloud backup feature, the Home Assistant team and the Nabu Casa team are now working closely together on a comprehensive revamp of backup integrations, to create an easy one-stop solution to a good backup strategy. We are also working to ensure users have a smooth onboarding for backing up to Home Assistant Cloud, as well as other third-party backup locations.</p>
<p>The team had to postpone some features in favor of others like <a href="/blog/2024/11/06/release-202411/#low-latency-cameras-using-webrtc">WebRTC</a>. They had successfully released the infrastructure needed to support WebRTC, both STUN servers for every Home Assistant user and TURN servers for every Home Assistant Cloud subscriber, enhancing real-time communication capabilities within Home Assistant. Two-factor authentication (2FA) is one of the postponed features, but it is still in the Nabu Casa pipeline.</p>
<h2>Open Protocols</h2>
<p>We remain committed to supporting open smart home standards, including Z-Wave Zigbee, Matter, and Thread, aligning with our Open Home mission to offer choice, privacy, and sustainability through locally controlled, cloud-independent devices.</p>
<p>In the past six months, we have made significant steps towards certifications, ensuring our open standards implementations are up to industry standards.</p>
<h3>Z-Wave</h3>
<p>In <a href="/blog/2024/09/24/we-are-joining-the-z-wave-alliance-board/">September</a>, Paulus, the founder of Home Assistant, announced his new role on the Z-Wave Alliance Board of Directors, representing Nabu Casa. Serving on the board will allow Nabu Casa to contribute meaningfully to Z-Wave’s development and ensure that the needs of Home Assistant users and open-source values are represented.</p>
<p>As interest in Z-Wave devices in our ecosystem continues to grow, this has driven Home Assistant to advance the Z-Wave JS stack and create its own Z-Wave hardware. While we are working on the <a href="/blog/2024/05/08/zwave-is-not-dead">certification of our Z-Wave implementation</a>, our work on building our own Z-Wave antenna has also been progressing smoothly. We base the design of our antenna on the <a href="https://github.com/drzwave/ZRAD">Z-Wave Reference Application Design</a> to create a Z-Wave antenna with the best performance in the market.</p>
<h3>Matter</h3>
<p>As one of the first in the industry, in June, we proudly announced that Home Assistant is now based on the <a href="/blog/2024/06/05/release-20246/#matter-turns-13">latest Matter 1.3 specification</a>. Since then, we continued to update our Matter implementation to improve the reliability and compatibility of Matter devices, and Matter certification should hopefully happen any day now soon!</p>
<p>We have brought expanded device support and performance improvements to Home Assistant’s Matter integration. Air purifiers, room air conditioners, and thermostats are now better supported, along with custom clusters, which allow Home Assistant to detect data changes in real-time, improving network efficiency.</p>
<p>Update entities now provide firmware updates via official Matter update channels, while event entities provide more event types, allowing you to react to single-press or double-press events with ease. Additional features include water valve support, operation state tracking for appliances, and smoke and CO sensor integration. Matter 1.3 power and energy sensors are also supported, providing useful data for the energy dashboard.</p>
<p>In the meantime, we will continue to work on Matter 1.4 compatibility, as well as making device commissioning easier and working with Thread credentials. We have made major strides forward and hopefully we will be able to get through some of our roadblocks soon.</p>
<h3>Zigbee</h3>
<p>The Zigbee Home Automation (ZHA) integration got a massive overhaul <a href="/blog/2024/08/07/release-20248/#zigbee-home-automation-zha-updates">during Summer</a>. The whole integration has been split into a separate codebase, making it easier to maintain and improve. This is a huge step forward for the integration, and took months of work to get done. This change will make the integration easier to maintain and improve in the future, including allowing code contributors to contribute more easily.</p>
<h2>What’s next?</h2>
<p>We hope that you can feel the results of all this work.  Given the positive feedback we have received from our users, we will continue to follow our roadmap to work on the next product initiatives.</p>
<p>We will also start preparing for the roadmap for next year. It will have a new theme, and we would like to have our community be more involved in the process of its creation. Planning has already begun, and we hope to announce it at the next State of the Open Home. Last but not the least, please get in the comments and give us your feedback - we read it all!</p>
<p>See you next year!</p>
<p>- <a href="https://github.com/Madelena">Madelena</a> &amp; <a href="https://github.com/jlpouffier">JLo</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Roadmap 2024 Midyear Update: A home-approved smart home, peace of mind, and more!]]></title>
    <link href="https://ivangrod.github.io/blog/2024/06/12/roadmap-2024h1/"/>
    <updated>2024-06-12T00:00:01+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://ivangrod.github.io/blog/2024/06/12/roadmap-2024h1</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src='/images/blog/2024-06-roadmap-2024h1/banner.png' class='no-shadow' alt='Banner for Roadmap 2024 Midyear Update'/></p>
<p>During our <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=oa__fLArsFk&amp;t=7649s">State of the Open Home livestream</a> in April, we presented our roadmaps for Home Assistant, open protocols, and Home Assistant Cloud. If you’re not sure what a roadmap is, or why we aren’t just listing features and dates - please read our intro to <a href="/blog/2024/06/12/roadmap-introduction">Home Assistant Roadmaps</a>.</p>
<p>There has already been a lot of great discussion about these roadmaps in the community, and we would really like to encourage you to give your thoughts in the comments of this blog - as they will inform <a href="/blog/2024/06/12/roadmap-introduction/#how-are-roadmaps-made">how the roadmap evolves over time</a>.</p>
<p>You can skip straight to the sections you’re most interested:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="#home-assistant-a-home-approved-smart-home">Home Assistant: “A Home-Approved Smart Home”</a></li>
<li><a href="#home-assistant-cloud-peace-of-mind">Home Assistant Cloud: “Peace of Mind”</a></li>
<li><a href="#open-standards-certified-quality">Open standards: “Certified Quality”</a></li>
</ul>
<p>~ <a href="https://github.com/madelena">Madelena</a> &amp; <a href="https://github.com/jlpouffier">JLo</a></p>
<p><em>Big thanks to everyone who had given feedback to us throughout the entire process!</em></p>
<!--more-->
<h2>Home Assistant: “A Home-Approved Smart Home”</h2>
<p><img src='/images/blog/2024-06-roadmap-2024h1/ha-roadmap-2024h1.png' class='no-shadow' alt="[Home Assistant Roadmap 2024 Midyear Update"/></p>
<p>The mission of the Home Assistant project is to become the best smart home platform that embodies the Open Home vision (privacy, choice, sustainability), powered by a helpful open-source user community.</p>
<p>A smart home platform should allow users to observe, control, automate, and anticipate the key functions within a home, which provides safety, security, comfort, convenience, personalization, and accessibility to its residents.</p>
<p>Through our user research, we learned that while Home Assistant is a powerful platform for people who prioritize better privacy and customizability, we also found that adoption within their homes is another story. Our users have often gone to great pains to make Home Assistant easier to use for other members of their household, either by using another app as the user interface or hiding any visible traces of the platform altogether. We call the adoption of Home Assistant by other household members the <a href="https://newsletter.openhomefoundation.org/open-home-approval-factor/">“Home Approval Factor”</a>.</p>
<p>Therefore, in the roadmap ahead for Home Assistant, we propose that our contributor community and us, the core maintainers, should focus our efforts on making Home Assistant more home-approved.  This can be done by improving the touchpoints that all members of the household will interact with, such as automations, dashboards, and voice assistants, while maintaining the power and depth of the platform for our power users and admins. Our plan is divided into the following areas:</p>
<h3>Dashboards</h3>
<p>We have been hard at work renovating our dashboards since last year. Moving forward, we are focused on making the dashboard user experience better for all users.</p>
<h4>Current priority: Make customization of dashboards easy and intuitive</h4>
<p>With the new Sections view layout, better tile cards, and our incredibly well-received <a href="/blog/2024/03/04/dashboard-chapter-1/">drag and drop</a> 🐉, we have recently begun our work on making dashboard customization easy and intuitive. We aim to implement an intuitive and organized grid system for dashboards. We will need community contributions to update our current cards to fit the grid system.</p>
<h4>Next priority: Make default dashboards more useful and relevant</h4>
<p>Our current default dashboard gives our users two choices: Either list every entity the system is connected to or start from scratch. With dashboard blueprints, we know that we can make the default dashboards more useful than that. We will need your input to optimize them to display the most relevant information from the get-go.</p>
<h4>Later priority: Improve privacy in user, guest, and public access</h4>
<p>The inability to fine-tune access to Home Assistant by guests or other members of the family has been a pain point requested by many of our users. We want to investigate ways to mitigate this while improving the privacy of the household.</p>
<h3>Voice assistants</h3>
<p>Since last year, we have built our voice assistant framework from scratch with our <a href="/blog/2022/12/20/year-of-voice/">“Year of the Voice”</a> initiative. Now that the infrastructure is in place, we want to make sure that it will be usable for everyone (before the demise of Alexa and Google Assistant 😜).</p>
<h4>Current priority 1: Improve Assist capabilities out of the box</h4>
<p>Our <a href="https://community.home-assistant.io/t/poll-what-do-you-use-your-voice-assistant-for-what-do-you-expect-it-to-do-multiple-selections/693669">research has shown</a> users are most interested in us improving out-of-the-box capabilities of Assist, for instance, timers, reminders, and music controls.</p>
<h4>Current priority 2: Make Assist easier to start with</h4>
<p>At the moment, there are several things you need to install or configure to get started with voice. We want to make it easier to set up and onboard. There are already some good hardware choices to start using voice, but we’re exploring building our voice satellite hardware to create a more plug-and-play experience.</p>
<h3>Automations</h3>
<p>Automation is one of the cornerstones of the home automation industry. The ability to automate your home so that it does what you expect when you expect it is both fascinating and extremely rewarding for users, regardless of their experience level. Today, the automation engine of Home Assistant is one of the most powerful in the market. However, this comes at a cost: It is not the simplest to approach.</p>
<h4>Current priority 1: Make automations easier to organize</h4>
<p>As users grow their smart home, they will create more automation. Our automations are listed in a large table and can get easily disorganized as it grows. Earlier this year, we did a lot to improve the organization of automations, including <a href="https://youtu.be/g3Xo0ArcMaY?si=OrqvNDASLFvyKhEs">labels, filters, and categories</a>, which in return not only made automations easier to organize, but also almost every table in the Home Assistant settings.</p>
<h4>Current priority 2: Make automations easier to create</h4>
<p>While we made headway earlier this year in making automations easier to create, we need a more comprehensive effort with a full product development cycle of research, discovery, ideation, and validation to confidently make design and implementation decisions. As of now, many seemingly simple automations can be too complex to create and debug, and there is a lot of room for improvement. We foresee that when this opportunity is done, admins and housemates can easily create automations.</p>
<hr />
<h3>Research</h3>
<p>To make informed product decisions, we need to base our work on solid research. Therefore, we have been building out our research capabilities, both in terms of user research and technology research.</p>
<h4>User research</h4>
<p>In order for all of us in our community to make the right product, design, and engineering decisions, we need all of us to have a clear picture of who our users really are. Last year, we did some initial research, mostly focused on dashboards. This year, we want to get the full picture with complete foundational research of our users.</p>
<p>Secondly, of the three Open Home values, privacy, choice, and sustainability, while we have a pretty solid understanding of choice and some understanding of sustainability, the idea of privacy can benefit from more clarity. We want a better understanding of what privacy really means to a home and its residents.</p>
<h4>Technology research (R&amp;D)</h4>
<p>Yes, large language models (LLMs) are a hot trend, but that’s not why we’re exploring them. We know there are very interesting problems they can solve in the home, and with the amount of data our users collect in their history, we believe that there is much power underneath Home Assistant yet to be unearthed and it is uniquely positioned to be the smart home platform for AI. <a href="/blog/2024/06/07/ai-agents-for-the-smart-home/">Our AI vision</a> lays down the foundation for what we want to do with AI and LLMs next.</p>
<p>In order to help AI make better decisions, we need a better understanding of the context of what each device actually is. To do so, we need to refine our information architecture. For instance, we recently rolled out floors helping Home Assistant better understand your house. This is no small task, but it could be vital in implementing better voice or even AI in the home.</p>
<hr />
<h2>Home Assistant Cloud: “Peace of Mind”</h2>
<p><a href="https://www.nabucasa.com/">Home Assistant Cloud</a>, powered by our commercial partner Nabu Casa brings, to the many, the hard-to-reach features of Home Assistant usually reserved for power users with expensive hardware at home, with no compromise on privacy.</p>
<p>Currently, Home Assistant Cloud provides the simplest and safest way to access your Home Assistant instance anywhere in the world and connect to third-party cloud-connected voice assistants, like Google’s and Alexa’s offerings. Our newest ability added to Cloud is the ability to offload the resource-intensive tasks of speech-to-text and text-to-speech. This allows our users to have power-efficient hardware at home, like the Home Assistant Green, which uses three watts and performs tasks usually reserved for hundred-watt home servers.</p>
<p>For the next phase of Home Assistant Cloud, we want to continue to build features that adhere to our mission, as stated above. The theme for the upcoming initiatives revolve around providing peace of mind for our users:</p>
<h4>Current priority: Hardening security</h4>
<p>We want to harden our security, providing more control for remote access and Two-Factor Authentication (2FA) for your Nabu Casa account.</p>
<h4>Next priority: Encrypted cloud backup</h4>
<p>This would allow users to have a more resilient installation of Home Assistant, so if your instance completely breaks down, it can be restored from the cloud.</p>
<h4>Later priority: Cloud monitoring</h4>
<p>If your Home Assistant instance goes down, we’ll be able to detect it and send an email notification. This will allow you to monitor your downtime, and hopefully avoid more of it in the future, keeping your whole family happy 😁.</p>
<p>If you are currently a subscriber of Home Assistant Cloud, thank you again for your generous support of our project, and please let us know what we can do to improve our service. If you haven’t subscribed yet, you can check it out <a href="https://nabucasa.com">here</a>!</p>
<hr />
<h2>Open standards: “Certified Quality”</h2>
<p>We believe open standards are critical to providing choices for the future of the open home, and that is why we have put a lot of work into supporting current and emerging standards. They provide a way for manufacturers to provide broad compatibility, but they also provide peace of mind for users by ensuring the longevity of the devices.</p>
<p>All our teams are currently working very hard on certification - we want to make sure all our open standards implementations are up to industry standards.</p>
<h3>Zigbee</h3>
<p>For Zigbee, we already have a well-established hardware solution via our <a href="/skyconnect/">Home Assistant Connect ZBT-1</a> (formerly known as the SkyConnect). We continue contributing code and refining ZHA and Zigpy, the software powering Zigbee in Home Assistant.</p>
<h3>Matter</h3>
<h4>Current priority 1: Certification</h4>
<p>Matter is served via our Matter Server, which is evolving with the standard, and we will continue to the first home automation system that adopts the latest Matter standards. Our Home Assistant Connect ZBT-1 hardware also supports this standard via its support of Matter over Thread.</p>
<h4>Current priority 2: Device Commissioning</h4>
<p>There are still some big challenges that need to be addressed like device commissioning, which is currently overly complex, and we’re working with the industry to improve this.</p>
<h3>Z-Wave</h3>
<h4>Current priority: Certification</h4>
<p>This year, we made several big announcements with our support of Z-Wave. We joined the Z-Wave Alliance in February this year and have been <a href="/blog/2024/05/08/zwave-is-not-dead">working to improve our Z-Wave JS software</a>.</p>
<h4>Next priority: Home Assistant Connect Hardware for Z-Wave</h4>
<p>To build the most seamless user experience for this protocol, we’re building our own Z-Wave stick to connect devices to Home Assistant. This new Z-Wave stick will join our Home Assistant Connect family of products.</p>
<hr />
<h2>What’s next?</h2>
<p>Our roadmap is an open call for contributions in the product areas we are focusing on. It outlines what the core maintainers of the Home Assistant project will work on in the near future. This is a tool for our contributors and us, the project maintainers, to plan ahead for our collective future. As this is a living document, we will revisit and update our roadmap every half year.</p>
<p>For more information on how the roadmaps were created and how you can contribute, please check out <a href="/blog/2024/06/12/roadmap-introduction">this blog post here</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A roadmap for Home Assistant]]></title>
    <link href="https://ivangrod.github.io/blog/2024/06/12/roadmap-introduction/"/>
    <updated>2024-06-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://ivangrod.github.io/blog/2024/06/12/roadmap-introduction</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p class="img no-shadow"><img src='/images/blog/2024-06-roadmap-introduction/art.jpg' alt='Artwork for the roadmap introduction'/><i>Art by Clelia Rella</i></p>
<p>During our <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=oa__fLArsFk&amp;t=7649s">State of the Open Home livestream</a>, we presented the future of the open home with the announcement of our first roadmap.</p>
<p>Over the past few years, we have begun the practice of giving a theme for the direction we wanted to take the Home Assistant project towards each year. Last year, we had the successful <a href="/blog/2022/12/20/year-of-voice/">Year of the Voice</a>, in which we built our voice assistant architecture from the ground up. And before that, we had “<a href="/blog/2022/01/19/streamlining-experiences/">Streamlining Experiences</a>” where we took our first stab at improving the UX.</p>
<p>Having a good set of goals allows us to focus our community and resources to build new projects rapidly together. With the Year of the Voice, we have attracted new contributors who are experts in wake words and voice technologies, translators of many languages, and hobbyists in building impressive one-of-a-kind voice assistants. We want to continue this success by laying out the strategy and direction for the continuous development of the Home Assistant project, and a product roadmap is a perfect tool for such a purpose.</p>
<p>Our roadmap is an open call for contributions in the product areas we are focusing on. Unlike many public roadmaps of commercial products, this is not a marketing ploy to attract customers to buy into nebulous, unrealized future features. It is a tool for our contributors and us, the project maintainers, to plan ahead for our collective future.</p>
<p>For this blog post, I’d like to detail how we came up with the roadmap, what it entails, and how you can build upon it together.</p>
<p>~ Madelena</p>
<!--more-->
<h2>Where can I find the roadmap?</h2>
<p>Our roadmaps will be published in our blog in the <a href="/blog/categories/roadmap/">Roadmap category</a>, this allows the community to provide feedback and discuss our direction in the forums easily.</p>
<p>Our first roadmap for midyear 2024, can be found <a href="/blog/2024/06/12/roadmap-2024h1/">here</a>.</p>
<h2>What is a roadmap?</h2>
<h3>What it is</h3>
<p>A roadmap provides the general direction of where we want to take our projects next, aka the “North Star” ⭐.</p>
<p>With existing products, it can be easy to operate on autopilot, especially when we are in a rhythm of building new features. Once in a while, it is important for us to understand the strategic context behind why we are doing what we are doing for our users, and figure out how we can get there in the long term.</p>
<p>A conversation about our roadmap with our community and users is an opportunity for us to verify our understanding of your needs before actually spending time and resources building them. Ideally, if we had done an excellent job in our user research, then the roadmap should merely confirm what you need, and there should be no surprises.</p>
<h3>What it is not</h3>
<p>We want to emphasize that this is <strong><em>not</em> a list of upcoming features</strong>, nor does it indicate the exact timeframe of when features will be built. We will not know the exact features we need to build until we have a good grasp of the problem encountered through user research. Usually, the closer the priority is, the clearer the picture is, and the more likely we know what features to build.</p>
<h2>What is on our roadmap?</h2>
<p>Our roadmap has three major elements: initiatives, themes, and timeframes.</p>
<h3>Initiatives</h3>
<p>Our roadmap contains the list of initiatives (also known as “product opportunities” for all you PM nerds) that we intend to work on, such as “making automations easier to organize”. They indicate the overall outcome that we want to achieve. Sometimes, there would be obvious features that we all know we should be working on, such as the most requested “drag and drop” feature in order to “make dashboards easier and more intuitive to customize and use”. Sometimes the answers aren’t as obvious, which is when user research would help us a great deal in providing clarity and helping us brainstorm solutions.</p>
<h3>Themes</h3>
<p>These initiatives are organized by themes, usually in the different product areas of the Home Assistant project, or by the common goal that these initiatives would achieve. To coordinate our efforts, each of these themes are usually led and driven by the same group of maintainers composed of developers, designers, and a product owner, who are passionate about the subject matter. For example, I love dashboards and that’s my current focus, while <a href="https://github.com/jlpouffier">@JLo</a> loves Assist and is making great strides in those areas with our contributors.</p>
<h3>Timeframes</h3>
<p>Our timeframes are divided roughly into what’s current, next, and later priorities. We decided against using exact dates because, on the one hand, guaranteeing a due date on features we might not even need to build puts unnecessary pressure on our maintainers. On the other hand, we cannot predict if or when our contributors will make contributions to our top initiatives. In general, a current priority is about three months, next is another three months after what’s current is done, and so on.</p>
<h2>How are roadmaps made?</h2>
<p>We want to make sure that this is an open source, open development, and open design process. So we, as the core project maintainers, will keep the dialog open to feedback and changes from our contributors and our community.</p>
<p>For our first roadmap in midyear 2024, we worked hard for 7 months to build it from scratch in the following steps:</p>
<ol>
<li>
<p><strong>Foundation</strong>: We make sure that our <a href="/blog/2016/01/19/perfect-home-automation/">founder’s vision</a> of what the best Home Assistant can be is reflected fully in the North Star of the roadmap. We also agree upon the purpose of the roadmap.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Collective feedback</strong>: After that, we met with the core project maintainers of various product areas, from frontend, voice, OS, documentation, open protocols, ESPHome, and more. We collected hundreds of problems that they know are the most concerning to our users and their ideas on how these problems can be solved. We also scoured and scanned through every top feature request on our forums and from previous Months of What the Heck. We collated them into one huge list of product issues we need to solve.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Prioritization</strong>: We organized and categorized these issues into various initiatives that we can pursue. Finally, we prioritized all these initiatives by the number of potential users who could benefit from them, how big an impact they can make, how certain we are in the issue, or if research is needed before proceeding. The final result is then organized into the roadmap that you see now.</p>
</li>
</ol>
<p>A roadmap is a <em>living document</em>, and we intend to adjust our bearings and revisit it every half-year. For instance, when we improve initiatives to an adequate level or if the needs of our users and community change, we will move our resources to focus on the next important priorities.</p>
<p>Our next update on the roadmap will be around late October to early November, after collecting your feedback from our infamous Month of What the Heck.</p>
<h2>How to use our roadmap</h2>
<p>As I mentioned before, our roadmap is not a list of future features, but an open call for contributions in the product areas we are focusing on.</p>
<p>If you would like to contribute to the Home Assistant project, I hope that our roadmap can provide you with ideas and guidance on what you can do. There are a number of ways you can support this journey. Let’s build the future of the Open Home together!</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p><strong>Develop</strong>: If you are a developer, of course you can contribute your code!</p>
<p>If you are an expert in the areas we are currently focused on in our roadmap, please feel free to reach out to us directly on <a href="/join-chat">Discord</a>. For example, if our current focus is to “improve voice assistant abilities out of the box” and if you were a wake word or LLM expert, that’s perfect! Please reach out and see where you can help.</p>
<p>If you know what you want to build, awesome! Be sure to check out our developer docs and learn about our <a href="https://developers.home-assistant.io/docs/review-process">review process</a>.</p>
<p>If you don’t have any ideas on what to code, please feel free to check out our <a href="https://github.com/home-assistant/core/issues">GitHub issues</a> and our <a href="https://community.home-assistant.io/c/feature-requests/13/l/latest?order=votes">top feature requests</a>. You may also chat with other folks on Discord to find out what needs your help the most.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Design</strong>: If you are a product person or a designer, we need you! Many of our features and contributions need great product goals, research, and design that solve real problems. Help us brainstorm ideas and solutions for the problems we want to solve on our roadmap, or report any new unforeseen problems that you notice in our community.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Participate in user research</strong>: If you and your housemates or family are interested, we would love to have you as part of our user research pool. From time to time, we will send out surveys or invite users to user interviews. This allows us to get an objective understanding of our users and validate and test our assumptions. Sign up to be part of the <a href="https://forms.clickup.com/2533032/f/2d9n8-12931/52N1KK00E9BXEW71TN">Home Assistant User Research Group</a>.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Guide our direction</strong>: As already mentioned, we use our <a href="https://community.home-assistant.io/c/feature-requests/">Feature Request</a> and <a href="https://community.home-assistant.io/c/what-the-heck/56">Month of What The Heck?</a> forums to guide the creation and prioritization of the roadmap. The number of votes and the amount of thoughtful discussions and creative ideas matter, so please participate in the threads and help guide the direction of our project.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>And that’s all you need to know about our roadmaps! Thanks for reading! Looking forward to collaborating with you on the Home Assistant project soon!</p>
<p>~ Madelena</p>
<h2>FAQ</h2>
<h4>1. I want feature X!</h4>
<p>Sure thing, we hear you. If you really want feature X, can you tell us and everyone in our community more about it, such as, what problems will this feature solve? Better yet, is it a recurring problem you have noticed that will help many other people? Use cases, research, and various evidence help us all decide whether we will proceed with such a feature. Make some noise on our forums, submit it to our feature requests, and see if it resonates with others. Maybe a contributor can help you out if the need is strong enough</p>
<h4>2. I think the Home Assistant project should go in direction Y.</h4>
<p>If you have a brilliant vision of what Home Assistant can become, please feel free to discuss them openly in the comments section of the roadmap, or post your thoughts on our forums. Our direction is determined by the collective needs of our users, guided by our Open Home values of privacy, choice, and sustainability. Any ideas that can benefit these areas may be considered to become part of our project vision.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
